<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4001/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4001/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-06T16:31:25+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Justin O’Brien</title><subtitle>Data Visualization • Analysis • Insights.  Exploring employment dynamics, career transitions, and economic trends through interactive visualizations and evidence-based research.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram" /><published>2025-08-01T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="visualizing-career-transitions-the-story-behind-the-sankey-diagram">Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram</h1>

<p>When I set out to visualize employment outcomes for professionals aged 50+ following redundancy, I knew the story was complex. Unlike a simple before-and-after comparison, career transitions unfold over time, with multiple pathways and outcomes that shift as months pass.</p>

<p>The <a href="/sankey.html">interactive Sankey diagram</a> I created tells this story through the flow of percentages across different time periods, revealing patterns that might be lost in traditional charts or tables.</p>

<h2 id="why-a-sankey-diagram">Why a Sankey Diagram?</h2>

<p>Sankey diagrams excel at showing flow and transition. They’re perfect for visualizing:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Proportional relationships</strong>: The width of each flow represents the percentage of people following that path</li>
  <li><strong>Multiple outcomes</strong>: Unlike pie charts that show a single moment, Sankey diagrams can show how outcomes evolve</li>
  <li><strong>Complex pathways</strong>: Some people find professional jobs quickly, others cycle through different states before settling into long-term outcomes</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-data-story">The Data Story</h2>

<p>The visualization reveals several key insights:</p>

<h3 id="early-struggles">Early Struggles</h3>

<p>At 3 months post-redundancy, 65% of professionals aged 50+ remain unemployed. This stark figure highlights the immediate challenge this demographic faces in the job market.</p>

<h3 id="gradual-recovery">Gradual Recovery</h3>

<p>By 6 months, the unemployment rate drops to 38%, and by 12 months to 30%. However, this recovery isn’t just about finding similar professional roles – it’s about adaptation and compromise.</p>

<h3 id="the-new-normal">The New Normal</h3>

<p>After 24 months, the data shows a “new normal” where:</p>

<ul>
  <li>45% eventually return to professional roles</li>
  <li>10% accept lower-paid positions</li>
  <li>15% become self-employed</li>
  <li>30% remain unemployed long-term</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="design-decisions">Design Decisions</h2>

<p>Several design choices enhance the storytelling:</p>

<h3 id="color-coding">Color Coding</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Blue</strong>: Professional employment (positive outcome)</li>
  <li><strong>Orange</strong>: Lower-paid employment (compromise outcome)</li>
  <li><strong>Green</strong>: Self-employment (alternative pathway)</li>
  <li><strong>Red</strong>: Unemployment (challenge outcome)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="gradients">Gradients</h3>

<p>Links between nodes use gradients that blend the source and target colors, visually representing the transition between different employment states.</p>

<h3 id="time-labels">Time Labels</h3>

<p>Clear time markers help users understand the progression and see how outcomes evolve over the critical first two years.</p>

<h3 id="responsive-design">Responsive Design</h3>

<p>The diagram adapts to different screen sizes while maintaining readability and impact.</p>

<h2 id="technical-implementation">Technical Implementation</h2>

<p>Built with D3.js and the d3-sankey plugin, the visualization processes flow data to create smooth, proportional connections between employment states across time periods.</p>

<p>Key technical features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Responsive SVG rendering</li>
  <li>Interactive tooltips showing exact percentages</li>
  <li>Hover effects to highlight specific flows</li>
  <li>Gradient definitions for smooth color transitions</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-broader-context">The Broader Context</h2>

<p>This visualization is part of a larger investigation into age-related employment challenges. The data combines insights from multiple sources including ONS statistics, Labour Force Survey data, and research from organizations like Ageing Better and the Resolution Foundation.</p>

<p>The goal isn’t just to present statistics, but to make the human impact of redundancy visible and understandable to policymakers, employers, and the affected individuals themselves.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>

<p>This Sankey diagram opens up several avenues for further exploration:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Regional variations in outcomes</li>
  <li>Industry-specific transition patterns</li>
  <li>The role of skills in successful transitions</li>
  <li>Interventions that improve outcomes</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m continuing to develop interactive tools that make employment data more accessible and actionable. Each visualization aims to bridge the gap between raw statistics and human understanding.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Interested in commissioning similar visualizations or discussing employment data analysis? <a href="/contact/">Get in touch</a> to explore collaboration opportunities.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="data-visualization" /><category term="employment" /><category term="sankey-diagram" /><category term="d3js" /><category term="career-transitions" /><category term="unemployment" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the design decisions and data insights behind the interactive Sankey diagram showing employment outcomes for professionals aged 50+ after redundancy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram" /><published>2025-08-01T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="visualizing-career-transitions-the-story-behind-the-sankey-diagram">Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram</h1>

<p>When I set out to visualize employment outcomes for professionals aged 50+ following redundancy, I knew the story was complex. Unlike a simple before-and-after comparison, career transitions unfold over time, with multiple pathways and outcomes that shift as months pass.</p>

<p>The <a href="/sankey.html">interactive Sankey diagram</a> I created tells this story through the flow of percentages across different time periods, revealing patterns that might be lost in traditional charts or tables.</p>

<h2 id="why-a-sankey-diagram">Why a Sankey Diagram?</h2>

<p>Sankey diagrams excel at showing flow and transition. They’re perfect for visualizing:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Proportional relationships</strong>: The width of each flow represents the percentage of people following that path</li>
  <li><strong>Multiple outcomes</strong>: Unlike pie charts that show a single moment, Sankey diagrams can show how outcomes evolve</li>
  <li><strong>Complex pathways</strong>: Some people find professional jobs quickly, others cycle through different states before settling into long-term outcomes</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-data-story">The Data Story</h2>

<p>The visualization reveals several key insights:</p>

<h3 id="early-struggles">Early Struggles</h3>

<p>At 3 months post-redundancy, 65% of professionals aged 50+ remain unemployed. This stark figure highlights the immediate challenge this demographic faces in the job market.</p>

<h3 id="gradual-recovery">Gradual Recovery</h3>

<p>By 6 months, the unemployment rate drops to 38%, and by 12 months to 30%. However, this recovery isn’t just about finding similar professional roles – it’s about adaptation and compromise.</p>

<h3 id="the-new-normal">The New Normal</h3>

<p>After 24 months, the data shows a “new normal” where:</p>

<ul>
  <li>45% eventually return to professional roles</li>
  <li>10% accept lower-paid positions</li>
  <li>15% become self-employed</li>
  <li>30% remain unemployed long-term</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="design-decisions">Design Decisions</h2>

<p>Several design choices enhance the storytelling:</p>

<h3 id="color-coding">Color Coding</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Blue</strong>: Professional employment (positive outcome)</li>
  <li><strong>Orange</strong>: Lower-paid employment (compromise outcome)</li>
  <li><strong>Green</strong>: Self-employment (alternative pathway)</li>
  <li><strong>Red</strong>: Unemployment (challenge outcome)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="gradients">Gradients</h3>

<p>Links between nodes use gradients that blend the source and target colors, visually representing the transition between different employment states.</p>

<h3 id="time-labels">Time Labels</h3>

<p>Clear time markers help users understand the progression and see how outcomes evolve over the critical first two years.</p>

<h3 id="responsive-design">Responsive Design</h3>

<p>The diagram adapts to different screen sizes while maintaining readability and impact.</p>

<h2 id="technical-implementation">Technical Implementation</h2>

<p>Built with D3.js and the d3-sankey plugin, the visualization processes flow data to create smooth, proportional connections between employment states across time periods.</p>

<p>Key technical features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Responsive SVG rendering</li>
  <li>Interactive tooltips showing exact percentages</li>
  <li>Hover effects to highlight specific flows</li>
  <li>Gradient definitions for smooth color transitions</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-broader-context">The Broader Context</h2>

<p>This visualization is part of a larger investigation into age-related employment challenges. The data combines insights from multiple sources including ONS statistics, Labour Force Survey data, and research from organizations like Ageing Better and the Resolution Foundation.</p>

<p>The goal isn’t just to present statistics, but to make the human impact of redundancy visible and understandable to policymakers, employers, and the affected individuals themselves.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>

<p>This Sankey diagram opens up several avenues for further exploration:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Regional variations in outcomes</li>
  <li>Industry-specific transition patterns</li>
  <li>The role of skills in successful transitions</li>
  <li>Interventions that improve outcomes</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m continuing to develop interactive tools that make employment data more accessible and actionable. Each visualization aims to bridge the gap between raw statistics and human understanding.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Interested in commissioning similar visualizations or discussing employment data analysis? <a href="/contact/">Get in touch</a> to explore collaboration opportunities.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="data-visualization" /><category term="employment" /><category term="sankey-diagram" /><category term="d3js" /><category term="career-transitions" /><category term="unemployment" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the design decisions and data insights behind the interactive Sankey diagram showing employment outcomes for professionals aged 50+ after redundancy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixing Universities: A Collective Approach to Financial Crisis</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixing Universities: A Collective Approach to Financial Crisis" /><published>2025-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities/"><![CDATA[<p>Universities in the UK are in trouble. Big trouble with pound signs.
Student fees are capped - Unis are paying about £3K a year to teach each student
Research is underfunded. Grants pay only about 70 pence of every research pound. Universities are funding their own research.
The once great bastions of soft power, stricter visa regulations have put off international students.</p>

<p>Let’s start with what won’t work.</p>
<ol>
  <li>The government won’t allow a higher fee cap. There’s no way they would allow the fee to pass the £10,000 ceiling given the state of student debt. It needs to go to £12K. This as been obvious since fees were introduced 15 years ago and immediately all universities charged the maximum allowed fee. No sign of “competition” between universities to teach cheaply. Why? ‘cos teaching is expensive when it involves actual teachers.</li>
  <li>The government won’t increase research spending more than a token amount. Never has happened, never will happen.</li>
  <li>The government won’t lift visa restrictions. The situation for international students will likely get worse rather than better.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="whats-been-tried-the-cutting-paradox">What’s Been Tried: The Cutting Paradox</h2>

<p><strong>Cut costs!</strong> Universities spend a lot on people. All kinds of staff. Cut them! Well, that’s what’s happening. What’s the result? A university that cuts say 500 staff across the board will get a short term benefit of saving the balance sheet for a year or two. It’s always more complicated than you’d think because it’s expensive to get rid of people - it’s a drawn out process that involves paying voluntary severances and compulsory redundancy payments. You may be cutting £30m from your annual budget but you also have to find £10m for all these one off payments. But what are the downsides of that short term balance sheet benefit? You have just made your university smaller. Long term your income is going to go down. You’ve done a sudden shrink in response to (widely predicted) circumstances. You can pretend that “efficiencies” and “productivity boosts” will mean you can do more with fewer staff. But when your staff are already working long hours amidst the threat of compulsory redundancy, how much more productive can you get? Probably LESS productive.</p>

<p>But, say senior managers struggling to get by on six figure salaries, there’s no other way to cut costs. We as a university have done everything we can!</p>

<p>This is a true, as a university you have done everything you can do.</p>

<p>But collectively, as a Universities UK, with 141 member institutions, you have done jack shit.</p>

<h2 id="the-ranking-tables-scam">The Ranking Tables Scam</h2>

<p>To get where we’re going, let’s start with the pointless waste of time and money that are University ranking tables, from eg The Guardian, The Times, The Good University Guide. Every year university PR teams pore over the newly published tables to find a statement that is vaguely accurate and sounds good - “proud to announce we’ve vaulted two places in the guide”, “now the highest rated institution … in north west suffolk”. The truth is that if you ignore the dumb ranks, and look at universities’ average scores over a few years they’re all pretty much the same. Wealthy universities do well, upstart institutions with no money do poorly. The rest are middling. Whisper it: there’s not much difference between them.</p>

<p>For all the money spent on marketing, promoting the unique aspects of the campus, the courses, the people, the buildings, the ethos, etc. Most universities in the UK teach mostly the same courses with the same content.</p>

<p>The problem with universities promoting themselves as unique institutions is that they do everything own their own. (because they’re unique!). Except they aren’t. They are all spending huge sums on the same things - Virtual Learning Environments, Digital Exams, Intranet platforms.</p>

<h2 id="the-15-billion-solution">The £1.5 Billion Solution</h2>

<p>In IT alone, 15% savings could be made by working together. Thats up to £250 million a year across the sector.</p>

<p>Universities claim they can’t do this, and must remain independent, citing competition-law concerns and autonomy. Competition Law is a not a problem. The IT service providers will lobby that it is, but this is where your letters to junior ministers come in.</p>

<p>And autonomy? do me a favour. Whose autonomy? “The university”.
The university should have “autonomy” to choose between say Moodle, Blackboard, Canvas and Brightspace for it’s online learning platform? What you mean is that senior management and a special working group wants autonomy. They want to flex their bulging senior management muscles. But for every single person who would actually use the system - the lectures putting crap on it, and the students using it - there is no autonomy at all. They have to use the system they’re provided.</p>

<p>It’s yet another example of the outdated and inefficient management structure of universities costing them millions.</p>

<p>And universities already use collective procurement through UK Universities Purchasing Consortia (UKPC), and other regional bodies. This currently saves about £500 million a year. Nice. but with full nationwide collective procurement, this could be tripled to about £1.5 billion per year. Which would be even nicer.</p>

<h2 id="a-case-study-ethics-systems">A Case Study: Ethics Systems</h2>

<p>Let’s look at a case study. Most universities in the UK use Infonetica Ethics RM for processing ethics applications for research with human participants. Most people who use these systems don’t know that because each university has a separate contract with Infonetica and brands their internal version with their own stupid name for it. It’s a generally slow and clunky system, but that’s common for IT in the education sector. As anyone who has ever applied for ethical approval on this system is only too well aware, it takes hours to figure out what do to and how to complete the online forms in a way that won’t result in multiple length rejections. And as anyone who has ever reviewed ethics applications submitted this way knows only too well, it takes far too long to review each problem and highlight the inconsistencies with uni policy.</p>

<p>This is for many reasons, usually related to the decisions originally made when the uni set up the system with Infonetica many years ago, and the complete lack of useful documentation. Fixing systems with bad UI and bad documentation is slow and expensive. So unis don’t do it. But if the same system is used across more than a 100 universities, each uni’s contribution to fixing the problem is now only 1% of the time and cost. It’s practically free.</p>

<h2 id="shared-teaching-materials">Shared Teaching Materials</h2>

<p>But I would go further than that. Above I noted that most university courses are the same. Does it matter where you study psychology, or mechanical engineering or history? Especially where there is an oversight body (eg the BPS for psychology), there are great similarities, let’s put it that way. so it’s perplexing why individual lecturers spend so many hundreds of hours duplicating the efforts of hundreds of other lecturers replicating similar teaching materials (slides, videos, handouts, worksheets) and assessments (exams, essays, mcqs etc). Modify a shared core, people. Saves time and money.</p>

<p>With all these savings, even in the current crisis in UK HE, there would have been no need for compulsory redundancies. None at all.</p>

<p>It’s too late to save me. But I’d like to think that lessons could be learned. Go out there and make this happen, people!</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-finance" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="funding-crisis" /><category term="collective-procurement" /><category term="shared-services" /><category term="education-policy" /><category term="institutional-efficiency" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Universities in the UK are in financial trouble. Instead of individual cost-cutting that shrinks institutions, the sector could save billions through collective action and smarter revenue diversification.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-02-fixing-universities/2025-08-01-fixing-universities/hero-university-finance.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-02-fixing-universities/2025-08-01-fixing-universities/hero-university-finance.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixing Universities: A Collective Approach to Financial Crisis</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixing Universities: A Collective Approach to Financial Crisis" /><published>2025-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities/"><![CDATA[<p>Universities in the UK are in trouble. Big trouble with pound signs.
Student fees are capped - Unis are paying about £3K a year to teach each student
Research is underfunded. Grants pay only about 70 pence of every research pound. Universities are funding their own research.
The once great bastions of soft power, stricter visa regulations have put off international students.</p>

<p>Let’s start with what won’t work.</p>
<ol>
  <li>The government won’t allow a higher fee cap. There’s no way they would allow the fee to pass the £10,000 ceiling given the state of student debt. It needs to go to £12K. This as been obvious since fees were introduced 15 years ago and immediately all universities charged the maximum allowed fee. No sign of “competition” between universities to teach cheaply. Why? ‘cos teaching is expensive when it involves actual teachers.</li>
  <li>The government won’t increase research spending more than a token amount. Never has happened, never will happen.</li>
  <li>The government won’t lift visa restrictions. The situation for international students will likely get worse rather than better.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="whats-been-tried-the-cutting-paradox">What’s Been Tried: The Cutting Paradox</h2>

<p><strong>Cut costs!</strong> Universities spend a lot on people. All kinds of staff. Cut them! Well, that’s what’s happening. What’s the result? A university that cuts say 500 staff across the board will get a short term benefit of saving the balance sheet for a year or two. It’s always more complicated than you’d think because it’s expensive to get rid of people - it’s a drawn out process that involves paying voluntary severances and compulsory redundancy payments. You may be cutting £30m from your annual budget but you also have to find £10m for all these one off payments. But what are the downsides of that short term balance sheet benefit? You have just made your university smaller. Long term your income is going to go down. You’ve done a sudden shrink in response to (widely predicted) circumstances. You can pretend that “efficiencies” and “productivity boosts” will mean you can do more with fewer staff. But when your staff are already working long hours amidst the threat of compulsory redundancy, how much more productive can you get? Probably LESS productive.</p>

<p>But, say senior managers struggling to get by on six figure salaries, there’s no other way to cut costs. We as a university have done everything we can!</p>

<p>This is a true, as a university you have done everything you can do.</p>

<p>But collectively, as a Universities UK, with 141 member institutions, you have done jack shit.</p>

<h2 id="the-ranking-tables-scam">The Ranking Tables Scam</h2>

<p>To get where we’re going, let’s start with the pointless waste of time and money that are University ranking tables, from eg The Guardian, The Times, The Good University Guide. Every year university PR teams pore over the newly published tables to find a statement that is vaguely accurate and sounds good - “proud to announce we’ve vaulted two places in the guide”, “now the highest rated institution … in north west suffolk”. The truth is that if you ignore the dumb ranks, and look at universities’ average scores over a few years they’re all pretty much the same. Wealthy universities do well, upstart institutions with no money do poorly. The rest are middling. Whisper it: there’s not much difference between them.</p>

<p>For all the money spent on marketing, promoting the unique aspects of the campus, the courses, the people, the buildings, the ethos, etc. Most universities in the UK teach mostly the same courses with the same content.</p>

<p>The problem with universities promoting themselves as unique institutions is that they do everything own their own. (because they’re unique!). Except they aren’t. They are all spending huge sums on the same things - Virtual Learning Environments, Digital Exams, Intranet platforms.</p>

<h2 id="the-15-billion-solution">The £1.5 Billion Solution</h2>

<p>In IT alone, 15% savings could be made by working together. Thats up to £250 million a year across the sector.</p>

<p>Universities claim they can’t do this, and must remain independent, citing competition-law concerns and autonomy. Competition Law is a not a problem. The IT service providers will lobby that it is, but this is where your letters to junior ministers come in.</p>

<p>And autonomy? do me a favour. Whose autonomy? “The university”.
The university should have “autonomy” to choose between say Moodle, Blackboard, Canvas and Brightspace for it’s online learning platform? What you mean is that senior management and a special working group wants autonomy. They want to flex their bulging senior management muscles. But for every single person who would actually use the system - the lectures putting crap on it, and the students using it - there is no autonomy at all. They have to use the system they’re provided.</p>

<p>It’s yet another example of the outdated and inefficient management structure of universities costing them millions.</p>

<p>And universities already use collective procurement through UK Universities Purchasing Consortia (UKPC), and other regional bodies. This currently saves about £500 million a year. Nice. but with full nationwide collective procurement, this could be tripled to about £1.5 billion per year. Which would be even nicer.</p>

<h2 id="a-case-study-ethics-systems">A Case Study: Ethics Systems</h2>

<p>Let’s look at a case study. Most universities in the UK use Infonetica Ethics RM for processing ethics applications for research with human participants. Most people who use these systems don’t know that because each university has a separate contract with Infonetica and brands their internal version with their own stupid name for it. It’s a generally slow and clunky system, but that’s common for IT in the education sector. As anyone who has ever applied for ethical approval on this system is only too well aware, it takes hours to figure out what do to and how to complete the online forms in a way that won’t result in multiple length rejections. And as anyone who has ever reviewed ethics applications submitted this way knows only too well, it takes far too long to review each problem and highlight the inconsistencies with uni policy.</p>

<p>This is for many reasons, usually related to the decisions originally made when the uni set up the system with Infonetica many years ago, and the complete lack of useful documentation. Fixing systems with bad UI and bad documentation is slow and expensive. So unis don’t do it. But if the same system is used across more than a 100 universities, each uni’s contribution to fixing the problem is now only 1% of the time and cost. It’s practically free.</p>

<h2 id="shared-teaching-materials">Shared Teaching Materials</h2>

<p>But I would go further than that. Above I noted that most university courses are the same. Does it matter where you study psychology, or mechanical engineering or history? Especially where there is an oversight body (eg the BPS for psychology), there are great similarities, let’s put it that way. so it’s perplexing why individual lecturers spend so many hundreds of hours duplicating the efforts of hundreds of other lecturers replicating similar teaching materials (slides, videos, handouts, worksheets) and assessments (exams, essays, mcqs etc). Modify a shared core, people. Saves time and money.</p>

<p>With all these savings, even in the current crisis in UK HE, there would have been no need for compulsory redundancies. None at all.</p>

<p>It’s too late to save me. But I’d like to think that lessons could be learned. Go out there and make this happen, people!</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-finance" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="funding-crisis" /><category term="collective-procurement" /><category term="shared-services" /><category term="education-policy" /><category term="institutional-efficiency" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Universities in the UK are in financial trouble. Instead of individual cost-cutting that shrinks institutions, the sector could save billions through collective action and smarter revenue diversification.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-02-fixing-universities/2025-08-01-fixing-universities/hero-university-finance.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-02-fixing-universities/2025-08-01-fixing-universities/hero-university-finance.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beating The Odds: Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beating The Odds: Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo" /><published>2025-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" alt="Professional looking person with graphs and career pathway charts in background" /></p>

<h2 id="four-months-in-mid-life-employment-limbo">Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo</h2>

<p>I was made redundant 4 months ago today.</p>

<p><strong>31 March:</strong> I executed the traditional farewell ritual of the mid-career professional: an almost-imperceptible shrug in the general direction of the photocopier and a short walk to the car park. No speeches, no novelty cake, not even a limp balloon. Just me, a cardboard box and the sort of existential soundtrack you normally get in French cinema.</p>

<p><strong>1 April:</strong> New month, new life. I was up with the larks, pounding the cross-trainer in a heroic attempt to sculpt a “new me”. Resistance machines were conquered, endorphins flowed, and—for a glorious forty-eight hours—I was basically the poster child for Mid-Life Reinvention.</p>

<p><strong>3 April:</strong> Doughnuts happened. Then ice cream. If Ben &amp; Jerry ever need to boost quarterly sales, they should simply make more fifty-somethings redundant; we’ll do the heavy lifting.</p>

<p>Fast-forward four months: zero salary, zero job, and—rather paradoxically—a very busy diary. I’ve uploaded a few LinkedIn posts and articles, but that’s the tip of the iceberg. It turns out that finding work in 2025 is very different from the last time I was in the job market. That was when Mark Zuckerberg was still in high school, Elon Musk had yet to be fired from PayPal, and Google was a long way from becoming a verb.</p>

<p>So what’s it actually like, drifting through middle-age employment limbo with a gym membership you no longer use and a freezer full of salted-caramel regret?</p>

<p><strong>It’s actually not too bad, apart from the whole zero salary thing.</strong></p>

<h2 id="the-numbers-game">The Numbers Game</h2>

<p>And I’m not alone. Exiting a professional job in your fifties (unwillingly) is not a rare occurrence, especially in 2025.</p>

<p>To figure out what happens next, I turned not to necromancy or tarot cards but to statistics and data visualisation. I’ve done a little research, the sources for which you’ll find at the end of this article. There isn’t a single definitive source of data so I’ve extracted some figures and done some careful extrapolation. And guesswork.</p>

<iframe src="/sankey.html" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" style="border: 1px solid #ddd; border-radius: 8px; margin: 20px 0;"></iframe>

<h3 id="figure-1-career-pathways-after-redundancy-at-50">Figure 1. Career Pathways After Redundancy at 50+</h3>

<p>Should I be worried that after 4 months I don’t have a job - any job? Not really. Only <strong>14% of my age group have another professional job within 3 months</strong> of leaving the old one. Another 14% are in lower paid work, and 7% say they’re “self-employed”, but <strong>two thirds are still jobless</strong>.</p>

<p>This jobless figure does drop and two years after redundancy only 20% are unemployed, although long term this goes up to nearly a third.</p>

<p>Should I be concerned that the odds are against me: I have a <strong>less than evens chance</strong> of landing in a professional job sometime in the next few years?</p>

<h2 id="understanding-the-odds">Understanding the Odds</h2>

<p>Some people resist any discussion of probability, preferring an unexamined optimism that screens out unfavourable statistics. I take the opposite view: the more granular the data—baseline rates, confidence intervals, omitted caveats—the better. Equipped with that information, we can assess alternatives rationally rather than intuitively.</p>

<p>For me, this is what it means to <strong>beat the odds</strong>. It is not a matter of willing a coin to land heads or expecting double-sixes on demand; it is a systematic appraisal of the distribution of outcomes under different courses of action and an informed adjustment of strategy in light of those probabilities.</p>

<p><strong>Chance remains a constant, but its impact can be moderated when we understand, rather than ignore, the numbers.</strong></p>

<p>There’s much more to say about what these figures tell us, but even I know that an article full of numbers should be brief.</p>

<h2 id="your-turn">Your Turn</h2>

<p>How did your own post-redundancy odds play out? Drop a note below—stats or stories equally welcome.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="sources">Sources</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Centre for Ageing Better, Work</td>
          <td>State of Ageing in 2020 – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/work-state-ageing-2020">ageing-better.org.uk/work-state-ageing-2020</a></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Resolution Foundation, A U-shaped crisis: the impact of the COVID-19 crisis on older workers – <a href="https://www.resolutionfoundation.org/publications/a-u-shaped-crisis/">resolutionfoundation.org/publications/a-u-shaped-crisis</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Resolution Foundation, “COVID-19 crisis has caused the biggest annual employment fall for older workers since the 1980s” – <a href="https://www.resolutionfoundation.org/press-releases/covid-19-crisis-has-caused-the-biggest-annual-employment-fall-for-older-workers-since-the-1980s/">resolutionfoundation.org/press-releases</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Guardian, “Over-50s who lose jobs much more likely to stay unemployed, study finds” – <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2021/jan/18/over-50s-who-lose-jobs-much-more-likely-to-stay-unemployed-study-finds">theguardian.com/society/2021/jan/18</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Rest Less, “Redundancies Amongst the Over 50s Have Nearly Tripled in a Year” – <a href="https://wiseage.org.uk/2021/04/redundancies-amongst-the-over-50s-have-nearly-tripled-in-a-year/">wiseage.org.uk/2021/04</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Centre for Ageing Better, Redundancy support for Over 50s – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/redundancy-support-over-50s">ageing-better.org.uk/redundancy-support-over-50s</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Office for National Statistics, Analysis of Job Changers and Stayers – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/uksectoraccounts/compendium/economicreview/april2019/analysisofjobchangersandstayers">ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Centre for Ageing Better, The State of Ageing 2022 – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/state-of-ageing">ageing-better.org.uk/state-of-ageing</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Office for National Statistics, Dataset RED02: Redundancies by age, industry and region – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peoplenotinwork/redundancies/datasets/redundanciesbyindustryagesexandreemploymentratesred02">ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>Office for National Statistics, Employment in the UK: July 2025 bulletin – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/employmentintheuk/july2025">ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="employment" /><category term="career" /><category term="redundancy" /><category term="job-search" /><category term="over-50s" /><category term="unemployment" /><category term="career-transition" /><category term="employment-statistics" /><category term="professional-development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was made redundant 4 months ago today. Fast-forward four months: zero salary, zero job, and—rather paradoxically—a very busy diary. So what's it actually like, drifting through middle-age employment limbo with a gym membership you no longer use and a freezer full of salted-caramel regret?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beating The Odds: Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beating The Odds: Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo" /><published>2025-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" alt="Professional looking person with graphs and career pathway charts in background" /></p>

<h2 id="four-months-in-mid-life-employment-limbo">Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo</h2>

<p>I was made redundant 4 months ago today.</p>

<p><strong>31 March:</strong> I executed the traditional farewell ritual of the mid-career professional: an almost-imperceptible shrug in the general direction of the photocopier and a short walk to the car park. No speeches, no novelty cake, not even a limp balloon. Just me, a cardboard box and the sort of existential soundtrack you normally get in French cinema.</p>

<p><strong>1 April:</strong> New month, new life. I was up with the larks, pounding the cross-trainer in a heroic attempt to sculpt a “new me”. Resistance machines were conquered, endorphins flowed, and—for a glorious forty-eight hours—I was basically the poster child for Mid-Life Reinvention.</p>

<p><strong>3 April:</strong> Doughnuts happened. Then ice cream. If Ben &amp; Jerry ever need to boost quarterly sales, they should simply make more fifty-somethings redundant; we’ll do the heavy lifting.</p>

<p>Fast-forward four months: zero salary, zero job, and—rather paradoxically—a very busy diary. I’ve uploaded a few LinkedIn posts and articles, but that’s the tip of the iceberg. It turns out that finding work in 2025 is very different from the last time I was in the job market. That was when Mark Zuckerberg was still in high school, Elon Musk had yet to be fired from PayPal, and Google was a long way from becoming a verb.</p>

<p>So what’s it actually like, drifting through middle-age employment limbo with a gym membership you no longer use and a freezer full of salted-caramel regret?</p>

<p><strong>It’s actually not too bad, apart from the whole zero salary thing.</strong></p>

<h2 id="the-numbers-game">The Numbers Game</h2>

<p>And I’m not alone. Exiting a professional job in your fifties (unwillingly) is not a rare occurrence, especially in 2025.</p>

<p>To figure out what happens next, I turned not to necromancy or tarot cards but to statistics and data visualisation. I’ve done a little research, the sources for which you’ll find at the end of this article. There isn’t a single definitive source of data so I’ve extracted some figures and done some careful extrapolation. And guesswork.</p>

<iframe src="/sankey.html" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" style="border: 1px solid #ddd; border-radius: 8px; margin: 20px 0;"></iframe>

<h3 id="figure-1-career-pathways-after-redundancy-at-50">Figure 1. Career Pathways After Redundancy at 50+</h3>

<p>Should I be worried that after 4 months I don’t have a job - any job? Not really. Only <strong>14% of my age group have another professional job within 3 months</strong> of leaving the old one. Another 14% are in lower paid work, and 7% say they’re “self-employed”, but <strong>two thirds are still jobless</strong>.</p>

<p>This jobless figure does drop and two years after redundancy only 20% are unemployed, although long term this goes up to nearly a third.</p>

<p>Should I be concerned that the odds are against me: I have a <strong>less than evens chance</strong> of landing in a professional job sometime in the next few years?</p>

<h2 id="understanding-the-odds">Understanding the Odds</h2>

<p>Some people resist any discussion of probability, preferring an unexamined optimism that screens out unfavourable statistics. I take the opposite view: the more granular the data—baseline rates, confidence intervals, omitted caveats—the better. Equipped with that information, we can assess alternatives rationally rather than intuitively.</p>

<p>For me, this is what it means to <strong>beat the odds</strong>. It is not a matter of willing a coin to land heads or expecting double-sixes on demand; it is a systematic appraisal of the distribution of outcomes under different courses of action and an informed adjustment of strategy in light of those probabilities.</p>

<p><strong>Chance remains a constant, but its impact can be moderated when we understand, rather than ignore, the numbers.</strong></p>

<p>There’s much more to say about what these figures tell us, but even I know that an article full of numbers should be brief.</p>

<h2 id="your-turn">Your Turn</h2>

<p>How did your own post-redundancy odds play out? Drop a note below—stats or stories equally welcome.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="sources">Sources</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Centre for Ageing Better, Work</td>
          <td>State of Ageing in 2020 – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/work-state-ageing-2020">ageing-better.org.uk/work-state-ageing-2020</a></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Resolution Foundation, A U-shaped crisis: the impact of the COVID-19 crisis on older workers – <a href="https://www.resolutionfoundation.org/publications/a-u-shaped-crisis/">resolutionfoundation.org/publications/a-u-shaped-crisis</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Resolution Foundation, “COVID-19 crisis has caused the biggest annual employment fall for older workers since the 1980s” – <a href="https://www.resolutionfoundation.org/press-releases/covid-19-crisis-has-caused-the-biggest-annual-employment-fall-for-older-workers-since-the-1980s/">resolutionfoundation.org/press-releases</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Guardian, “Over-50s who lose jobs much more likely to stay unemployed, study finds” – <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2021/jan/18/over-50s-who-lose-jobs-much-more-likely-to-stay-unemployed-study-finds">theguardian.com/society/2021/jan/18</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Rest Less, “Redundancies Amongst the Over 50s Have Nearly Tripled in a Year” – <a href="https://wiseage.org.uk/2021/04/redundancies-amongst-the-over-50s-have-nearly-tripled-in-a-year/">wiseage.org.uk/2021/04</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Centre for Ageing Better, Redundancy support for Over 50s – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/redundancy-support-over-50s">ageing-better.org.uk/redundancy-support-over-50s</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Office for National Statistics, Analysis of Job Changers and Stayers – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/uksectoraccounts/compendium/economicreview/april2019/analysisofjobchangersandstayers">ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Centre for Ageing Better, The State of Ageing 2022 – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/state-of-ageing">ageing-better.org.uk/state-of-ageing</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Office for National Statistics, Dataset RED02: Redundancies by age, industry and region – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peoplenotinwork/redundancies/datasets/redundanciesbyindustryagesexandreemploymentratesred02">ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>Office for National Statistics, Employment in the UK: July 2025 bulletin – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/employmentintheuk/july2025">ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="employment" /><category term="career" /><category term="redundancy" /><category term="job-search" /><category term="over-50s" /><category term="unemployment" /><category term="career-transition" /><category term="employment-statistics" /><category term="professional-development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was made redundant 4 months ago today. Fast-forward four months: zero salary, zero job, and—rather paradoxically—a very busy diary. So what's it actually like, drifting through middle-age employment limbo with a gym membership you no longer use and a freezer full of salted-caramel regret?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Murder a University: A Guide to Institutional Death</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Murder a University: A Guide to Institutional Death" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent posts I’ve already skipped indelicately through Britain’s higher-education money-pit, tutted at missed savings, and poked the soggy bits of management. “Cheer up,” I promised. So naturally it’s time to talk about death. Not yours, happily, but the demise of an entire university – a topic so bleak it makes actuarial tables look frisky.</p>

<h2 id="the-impossible-dream-of-university-death">The Impossible Dream of University Death</h2>

<p>Universities are remarkably difficult to kill. Unlike your corner shop or local restaurant, they cannot simply lock the doors and disappear into the night. They are typically incorporated as charitable entities with Royal Charters or established under specific legislation, making them about as easy to dissolve as the House of Lords (and roughly as likely to happen).</p>

<h2 id="the-office-for-students-university-undertaker">The Office for Students: University Undertaker</h2>

<p>When a university starts circling the financial drain, the Office for Students (OfS) swoops in like a particularly bureaucratic grim reaper. Their powers include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Financial monitoring:</strong> Think of it as a fiscal heart monitor, beeping increasingly urgently</li>
  <li><strong>Intervention orders:</strong> Forcing universities to accept external governance</li>
  <li><strong>Student protection:</strong> Ensuring current students can complete their studies elsewhere</li>
  <li><strong>Revocation of degree-awarding powers:</strong> The academic equivalent of cardiac arrest</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-legal-labyrinth">The Legal Labyrinth</h2>

<p>Closing a university involves navigating a maze of regulations that would make Kafka weep:</p>

<p><strong>Student Protection Plans:</strong> Every university must have a plan for what happens to students if the institution fails. It’s like a will for academic programs.</p>

<p><strong>Asset Distribution:</strong> University assets cannot be sold for private profit—they must be transferred to other charitable or educational purposes.</p>

<p><strong>Staff and Pension Obligations:</strong> Universities cannot simply abandon employment contracts or pension commitments.</p>

<p><strong>Research Continuity:</strong> Ongoing research projects must be preserved or transferred, along with their ethical approvals and data.</p>

<h2 id="case-studies-in-institutional-mortality">Case Studies in Institutional Mortality</h2>

<p><strong>The University of Wales:</strong> Not technically dead, but so diminished it’s essentially academic roadkill. Once a federal university overseeing multiple institutions, it’s now reduced to validating degrees for overseas partners.</p>

<p><strong>London Metropolitan University:</strong> Nearly died in 2012 when it lost its license to sponsor international students. Survived, but only after dramatic restructuring and significant downsizing.</p>

<h2 id="the-zombie-university-scenario">The Zombie University Scenario</h2>

<p>The most likely outcome for failing universities isn’t death but zombification: institutions that continue to exist but have lost their essential functions. They limp along with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Dramatically reduced course offerings</li>
  <li>Skeleton staff</li>
  <li>Crumbling infrastructure</li>
  <li>Diminished research capacity</li>
  <li>Reputation in free fall</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="financial-rigor-mortis">Financial Rigor Mortis</h2>

<p>Universities experience financial death in stages:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Cash flow problems:</strong> Late payment of bills, delayed salaries</li>
  <li><strong>Credit downgrades:</strong> Banks start demanding higher interest rates</li>
  <li><strong>Regulatory intervention:</strong> OfS imposes external oversight</li>
  <li><strong>Student recruitment collapse:</strong> Nobody wants to enroll at a failing institution</li>
  <li><strong>Staff exodus:</strong> Academics flee to more stable institutions</li>
  <li><strong>Academic rigor mortis:</strong> The institution cannot fulfill its core functions</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-political-dimension">The Political Dimension</h2>

<p>No government wants to be responsible for closing universities, especially ones with significant local economic impact. This political reality means that failing institutions often receive:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Emergency loans</li>
  <li>Merger opportunities with stronger partners</li>
  <li>Gradual managed decline rather than sudden closure</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="prevention-better-than-cure">Prevention Better Than Cure</h2>

<p>The best way to avoid institutional death is early intervention:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Realistic financial planning:</strong> Based on actual revenue, not wishful thinking</li>
  <li><strong>Diversified income streams:</strong> Not relying solely on tuition fees</li>
  <li><strong>Strategic partnerships:</strong> Sharing costs and risks with other institutions</li>
  <li><strong>Regular health checks:</strong> Financial monitoring before crisis hits</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion-the-undead-academy">Conclusion: The Undead Academy</h2>

<p>In practice, university “death” is more often a transformation into something unrecognizable than actual closure. The institution may survive, but its soul—the ability to provide quality education and research—may be long gone.</p>

<p>Perhaps the real question isn’t how to kill a university, but how to keep it truly alive. In an era of financial pressure and political interference, that might be the greater challenge.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-governance" /><category term="insolvency" /><category term="university-closure" /><category term="OfS-regulation" /><category term="insolvency-law" /><category term="student-protection" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="institutional-failure" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A UK university cannot simply press CTRL-ALT-DELETE and vanish. Here's what actually happens when institutions reach the end of the financial road.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Closure" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Closure" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Murder a University: A Guide to Institutional Death</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Murder a University: A Guide to Institutional Death" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent posts I’ve already skipped indelicately through Britain’s higher-education money-pit, tutted at missed savings, and poked the soggy bits of management. “Cheer up,” I promised. So naturally it’s time to talk about death. Not yours, happily, but the demise of an entire university – a topic so bleak it makes actuarial tables look frisky.</p>

<h2 id="the-impossible-dream-of-university-death">The Impossible Dream of University Death</h2>

<p>Universities are remarkably difficult to kill. Unlike your corner shop or local restaurant, they cannot simply lock the doors and disappear into the night. They are typically incorporated as charitable entities with Royal Charters or established under specific legislation, making them about as easy to dissolve as the House of Lords (and roughly as likely to happen).</p>

<h2 id="the-office-for-students-university-undertaker">The Office for Students: University Undertaker</h2>

<p>When a university starts circling the financial drain, the Office for Students (OfS) swoops in like a particularly bureaucratic grim reaper. Their powers include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Financial monitoring:</strong> Think of it as a fiscal heart monitor, beeping increasingly urgently</li>
  <li><strong>Intervention orders:</strong> Forcing universities to accept external governance</li>
  <li><strong>Student protection:</strong> Ensuring current students can complete their studies elsewhere</li>
  <li><strong>Revocation of degree-awarding powers:</strong> The academic equivalent of cardiac arrest</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-legal-labyrinth">The Legal Labyrinth</h2>

<p>Closing a university involves navigating a maze of regulations that would make Kafka weep:</p>

<p><strong>Student Protection Plans:</strong> Every university must have a plan for what happens to students if the institution fails. It’s like a will for academic programs.</p>

<p><strong>Asset Distribution:</strong> University assets cannot be sold for private profit—they must be transferred to other charitable or educational purposes.</p>

<p><strong>Staff and Pension Obligations:</strong> Universities cannot simply abandon employment contracts or pension commitments.</p>

<p><strong>Research Continuity:</strong> Ongoing research projects must be preserved or transferred, along with their ethical approvals and data.</p>

<h2 id="case-studies-in-institutional-mortality">Case Studies in Institutional Mortality</h2>

<p><strong>The University of Wales:</strong> Not technically dead, but so diminished it’s essentially academic roadkill. Once a federal university overseeing multiple institutions, it’s now reduced to validating degrees for overseas partners.</p>

<p><strong>London Metropolitan University:</strong> Nearly died in 2012 when it lost its license to sponsor international students. Survived, but only after dramatic restructuring and significant downsizing.</p>

<h2 id="the-zombie-university-scenario">The Zombie University Scenario</h2>

<p>The most likely outcome for failing universities isn’t death but zombification: institutions that continue to exist but have lost their essential functions. They limp along with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Dramatically reduced course offerings</li>
  <li>Skeleton staff</li>
  <li>Crumbling infrastructure</li>
  <li>Diminished research capacity</li>
  <li>Reputation in free fall</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="financial-rigor-mortis">Financial Rigor Mortis</h2>

<p>Universities experience financial death in stages:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Cash flow problems:</strong> Late payment of bills, delayed salaries</li>
  <li><strong>Credit downgrades:</strong> Banks start demanding higher interest rates</li>
  <li><strong>Regulatory intervention:</strong> OfS imposes external oversight</li>
  <li><strong>Student recruitment collapse:</strong> Nobody wants to enroll at a failing institution</li>
  <li><strong>Staff exodus:</strong> Academics flee to more stable institutions</li>
  <li><strong>Academic rigor mortis:</strong> The institution cannot fulfill its core functions</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-political-dimension">The Political Dimension</h2>

<p>No government wants to be responsible for closing universities, especially ones with significant local economic impact. This political reality means that failing institutions often receive:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Emergency loans</li>
  <li>Merger opportunities with stronger partners</li>
  <li>Gradual managed decline rather than sudden closure</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="prevention-better-than-cure">Prevention Better Than Cure</h2>

<p>The best way to avoid institutional death is early intervention:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Realistic financial planning:</strong> Based on actual revenue, not wishful thinking</li>
  <li><strong>Diversified income streams:</strong> Not relying solely on tuition fees</li>
  <li><strong>Strategic partnerships:</strong> Sharing costs and risks with other institutions</li>
  <li><strong>Regular health checks:</strong> Financial monitoring before crisis hits</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion-the-undead-academy">Conclusion: The Undead Academy</h2>

<p>In practice, university “death” is more often a transformation into something unrecognizable than actual closure. The institution may survive, but its soul—the ability to provide quality education and research—may be long gone.</p>

<p>Perhaps the real question isn’t how to kill a university, but how to keep it truly alive. In an era of financial pressure and political interference, that might be the greater challenge.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-governance" /><category term="insolvency" /><category term="university-closure" /><category term="OfS-regulation" /><category term="insolvency-law" /><category term="student-protection" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="institutional-failure" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A UK university cannot simply press CTRL-ALT-DELETE and vanish. Here's what actually happens when institutions reach the end of the financial road.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Closure" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Closure" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond the Balance Sheet: Why UK Universities Need a Busyness Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond the Balance Sheet: Why UK Universities Need a Busyness Model" /><published>2025-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet/"><![CDATA[<p>Calling a university’s strategy its “business model” is a bit like calling the Royal Opera House a karaoke bar— both involve singing for money, but that’s where the resemblance ends. Yes, the UK sector’s fiscal plumbing is hissing ominously, but the ‘business model’ mantra pares back a sprawling public-good ecosystem until it resembles someone trying to fund science with a primary-school bake sale.</p>

<h2 id="the-problem-with-business-models">The Problem with Business Models</h2>

<p>Business models are designed to maximize shareholder value through efficient resource allocation and competitive advantage. Universities, by contrast, are charitable institutions designed to maximize public benefit through education, research, and knowledge transfer.</p>

<p>Trying to apply business model thinking to universities creates several problems:</p>

<p><strong>Short-term vs. Long-term Thinking:</strong> Businesses optimize for quarterly results; universities should optimize for generational impact.</p>

<p><strong>Measurable vs. Immeasurable Value:</strong> Business success is measured in profit margins; university success includes cultural preservation, scientific breakthrough, and social mobility.</p>

<p><strong>Competition vs. Collaboration:</strong> Business models assume zero-sum competition; universities create positive-sum knowledge that benefits everyone.</p>

<h2 id="enter-the-busyness-model">Enter the Busyness Model</h2>

<p>Instead of business models, universities need “busyness models”—frameworks that capture how they create value through being busy with meaningful work rather than just profitable work.</p>

<p>A busyness model would measure:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Research Impact:</strong> Not just publication counts, but real-world application</li>
  <li><strong>Educational Value:</strong> Not just graduate employment rates, but lifetime learning outcomes</li>
  <li><strong>Social Return:</strong> Not just economic contribution, but community development</li>
  <li><strong>Knowledge Exchange:</strong> Not just technology transfer, but cultural and intellectual enrichment</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-multiple-value-problem">The Multiple Value Problem</h2>

<p>Universities create multiple types of value simultaneously:</p>

<p><strong>Economic Value:</strong> Skilled graduates, research commercialization, local economic impact</p>

<p><strong>Social Value:</strong> Cultural preservation, social mobility, civic engagement</p>

<p><strong>Intellectual Value:</strong> New knowledge, critical thinking, artistic creation</p>

<p><strong>Long-term Value:</strong> Institutional memory, intergenerational knowledge transfer</p>

<p>Trying to reduce this to a simple business model is like trying to measure a symphony with a profit-and-loss statement.</p>

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h2>

<p>The business model obsession leads to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Cutting “unprofitable” subjects like philosophy and languages</li>
  <li>Prioritizing revenue-generating activities over educational quality</li>
  <li>Treating students as customers rather than scholars</li>
  <li>Focusing on measurable outcomes rather than transformational education</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="a-different-approach-social-return-on-investment">A Different Approach: Social Return on Investment</h2>

<p>Instead of business models, universities could use Social Return on Investment (SROI) frameworks that capture:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Direct Benefits:</strong> Graduate earnings, research commercialization</li>
  <li><strong>Indirect Benefits:</strong> Community development, cultural enrichment</li>
  <li><strong>Induced Benefits:</strong> Long-term societal transformation through education</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-ecosystem-perspective">The Ecosystem Perspective</h2>

<p>Universities exist within knowledge ecosystems, not business markets. They:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Share knowledge freely rather than hoarding competitive advantage</li>
  <li>Collaborate with institutions that might be considered “competitors”</li>
  <li>Create public goods that benefit society beyond their immediate stakeholders</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="international-examples">International Examples</h2>

<p><strong>Finland:</strong> Universities are funded based on broader societal outcomes, not just economic metrics.</p>

<p><strong>Germany:</strong> The dual system combines practical training with theoretical education, recognizing multiple forms of value.</p>

<p><strong>Canada:</strong> Provincial funding models incorporate community development and indigenous knowledge preservation.</p>

<h2 id="practical-steps">Practical Steps</h2>

<p>Universities could develop better busyness models by:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Measuring Social Impact:</strong> Tracking graduates’ civic engagement, not just employment</li>
  <li><strong>Valuing Knowledge Commons:</strong> Recognizing open research and public engagement</li>
  <li><strong>Community Integration:</strong> Measuring local economic and cultural development</li>
  <li><strong>Long-term Thinking:</strong> Planning for generational rather than annual outcomes</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="conclusion-beyond-the-bottom-line">Conclusion: Beyond the Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Universities are not businesses, and trying to make them behave like businesses destroys their essential public value. Instead of business models, they need busyness models that capture the full scope of their societal contribution.</p>

<p>The goal should not be to run universities like businesses, but to run them like the complex, valuable public institutions they are. That requires different metrics, different timeframes, and different definitions of success.</p>

<p>After all, the best universities have never been about efficiency—they’ve been about effectiveness at transforming both individuals and society. That’s a kind of busyness worth investing in.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-strategy" /><category term="public-value" /><category term="university-business-model" /><category term="SROI" /><category term="social-return-investment" /><category term="public-good" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="university-finance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Calling a university's strategy its 'business model' is like calling the Royal Opera House a karaoke bar. Universities need a busyness model focused on public value, not just profit margins.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-01-beyond-the-balance-sheet/busyness-banner.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-01-beyond-the-balance-sheet/busyness-banner.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond the Balance Sheet: Why UK Universities Need a Busyness Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond the Balance Sheet: Why UK Universities Need a Busyness Model" /><published>2025-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet/"><![CDATA[<p>Calling a university’s strategy its “business model” is a bit like calling the Royal Opera House a karaoke bar— both involve singing for money, but that’s where the resemblance ends. Yes, the UK sector’s fiscal plumbing is hissing ominously, but the ‘business model’ mantra pares back a sprawling public-good ecosystem until it resembles someone trying to fund science with a primary-school bake sale.</p>

<h2 id="the-problem-with-business-models">The Problem with Business Models</h2>

<p>Business models are designed to maximize shareholder value through efficient resource allocation and competitive advantage. Universities, by contrast, are charitable institutions designed to maximize public benefit through education, research, and knowledge transfer.</p>

<p>Trying to apply business model thinking to universities creates several problems:</p>

<p><strong>Short-term vs. Long-term Thinking:</strong> Businesses optimize for quarterly results; universities should optimize for generational impact.</p>

<p><strong>Measurable vs. Immeasurable Value:</strong> Business success is measured in profit margins; university success includes cultural preservation, scientific breakthrough, and social mobility.</p>

<p><strong>Competition vs. Collaboration:</strong> Business models assume zero-sum competition; universities create positive-sum knowledge that benefits everyone.</p>

<h2 id="enter-the-busyness-model">Enter the Busyness Model</h2>

<p>Instead of business models, universities need “busyness models”—frameworks that capture how they create value through being busy with meaningful work rather than just profitable work.</p>

<p>A busyness model would measure:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Research Impact:</strong> Not just publication counts, but real-world application</li>
  <li><strong>Educational Value:</strong> Not just graduate employment rates, but lifetime learning outcomes</li>
  <li><strong>Social Return:</strong> Not just economic contribution, but community development</li>
  <li><strong>Knowledge Exchange:</strong> Not just technology transfer, but cultural and intellectual enrichment</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-multiple-value-problem">The Multiple Value Problem</h2>

<p>Universities create multiple types of value simultaneously:</p>

<p><strong>Economic Value:</strong> Skilled graduates, research commercialization, local economic impact</p>

<p><strong>Social Value:</strong> Cultural preservation, social mobility, civic engagement</p>

<p><strong>Intellectual Value:</strong> New knowledge, critical thinking, artistic creation</p>

<p><strong>Long-term Value:</strong> Institutional memory, intergenerational knowledge transfer</p>

<p>Trying to reduce this to a simple business model is like trying to measure a symphony with a profit-and-loss statement.</p>

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h2>

<p>The business model obsession leads to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Cutting “unprofitable” subjects like philosophy and languages</li>
  <li>Prioritizing revenue-generating activities over educational quality</li>
  <li>Treating students as customers rather than scholars</li>
  <li>Focusing on measurable outcomes rather than transformational education</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="a-different-approach-social-return-on-investment">A Different Approach: Social Return on Investment</h2>

<p>Instead of business models, universities could use Social Return on Investment (SROI) frameworks that capture:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Direct Benefits:</strong> Graduate earnings, research commercialization</li>
  <li><strong>Indirect Benefits:</strong> Community development, cultural enrichment</li>
  <li><strong>Induced Benefits:</strong> Long-term societal transformation through education</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-ecosystem-perspective">The Ecosystem Perspective</h2>

<p>Universities exist within knowledge ecosystems, not business markets. They:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Share knowledge freely rather than hoarding competitive advantage</li>
  <li>Collaborate with institutions that might be considered “competitors”</li>
  <li>Create public goods that benefit society beyond their immediate stakeholders</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="international-examples">International Examples</h2>

<p><strong>Finland:</strong> Universities are funded based on broader societal outcomes, not just economic metrics.</p>

<p><strong>Germany:</strong> The dual system combines practical training with theoretical education, recognizing multiple forms of value.</p>

<p><strong>Canada:</strong> Provincial funding models incorporate community development and indigenous knowledge preservation.</p>

<h2 id="practical-steps">Practical Steps</h2>

<p>Universities could develop better busyness models by:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Measuring Social Impact:</strong> Tracking graduates’ civic engagement, not just employment</li>
  <li><strong>Valuing Knowledge Commons:</strong> Recognizing open research and public engagement</li>
  <li><strong>Community Integration:</strong> Measuring local economic and cultural development</li>
  <li><strong>Long-term Thinking:</strong> Planning for generational rather than annual outcomes</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="conclusion-beyond-the-bottom-line">Conclusion: Beyond the Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Universities are not businesses, and trying to make them behave like businesses destroys their essential public value. Instead of business models, they need busyness models that capture the full scope of their societal contribution.</p>

<p>The goal should not be to run universities like businesses, but to run them like the complex, valuable public institutions they are. That requires different metrics, different timeframes, and different definitions of success.</p>

<p>After all, the best universities have never been about efficiency—they’ve been about effectiveness at transforming both individuals and society. That’s a kind of busyness worth investing in.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-strategy" /><category term="public-value" /><category term="university-business-model" /><category term="SROI" /><category term="social-return-investment" /><category term="public-good" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="university-finance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Calling a university's strategy its 'business model' is like calling the Royal Opera House a karaoke bar. Universities need a busyness model focused on public value, not just profit margins.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-01-beyond-the-balance-sheet/busyness-banner.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-01-beyond-the-balance-sheet/busyness-banner.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>