<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4001/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4001/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-08-05T09:06:17+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Justin O’Brien</title><subtitle>Data Visualization • Analysis • Insights.  Exploring employment dynamics, career transitions, and economic trends through interactive visualizations and evidence-based research.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram" /><published>2025-08-01T11:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T11:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/visualizing-career-transitions/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="visualizing-career-transitions-the-story-behind-the-sankey-diagram">Visualizing Career Transitions: The Story Behind the Sankey Diagram</h1>

<p>When I set out to visualize employment outcomes for professionals aged 50+ following redundancy, I knew the story was complex. Unlike a simple before-and-after comparison, career transitions unfold over time, with multiple pathways and outcomes that shift as months pass.</p>

<p>The <a href="/sankey.html">interactive Sankey diagram</a> I created tells this story through the flow of percentages across different time periods, revealing patterns that might be lost in traditional charts or tables.</p>

<h2 id="why-a-sankey-diagram">Why a Sankey Diagram?</h2>

<p>Sankey diagrams excel at showing flow and transition. They’re perfect for visualizing:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Proportional relationships</strong>: The width of each flow represents the percentage of people following that path</li>
  <li><strong>Multiple outcomes</strong>: Unlike pie charts that show a single moment, Sankey diagrams can show how outcomes evolve</li>
  <li><strong>Complex pathways</strong>: Some people find professional jobs quickly, others cycle through different states before settling into long-term outcomes</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-data-story">The Data Story</h2>

<p>The visualization reveals several key insights:</p>

<h3 id="early-struggles">Early Struggles</h3>

<p>At 3 months post-redundancy, 65% of professionals aged 50+ remain unemployed. This stark figure highlights the immediate challenge this demographic faces in the job market.</p>

<h3 id="gradual-recovery">Gradual Recovery</h3>

<p>By 6 months, the unemployment rate drops to 38%, and by 12 months to 30%. However, this recovery isn’t just about finding similar professional roles – it’s about adaptation and compromise.</p>

<h3 id="the-new-normal">The New Normal</h3>

<p>After 24 months, the data shows a “new normal” where:</p>

<ul>
  <li>45% eventually return to professional roles</li>
  <li>10% accept lower-paid positions</li>
  <li>15% become self-employed</li>
  <li>30% remain unemployed long-term</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="design-decisions">Design Decisions</h2>

<p>Several design choices enhance the storytelling:</p>

<h3 id="color-coding">Color Coding</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Blue</strong>: Professional employment (positive outcome)</li>
  <li><strong>Orange</strong>: Lower-paid employment (compromise outcome)</li>
  <li><strong>Green</strong>: Self-employment (alternative pathway)</li>
  <li><strong>Red</strong>: Unemployment (challenge outcome)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="gradients">Gradients</h3>

<p>Links between nodes use gradients that blend the source and target colors, visually representing the transition between different employment states.</p>

<h3 id="time-labels">Time Labels</h3>

<p>Clear time markers help users understand the progression and see how outcomes evolve over the critical first two years.</p>

<h3 id="responsive-design">Responsive Design</h3>

<p>The diagram adapts to different screen sizes while maintaining readability and impact.</p>

<h2 id="technical-implementation">Technical Implementation</h2>

<p>Built with D3.js and the d3-sankey plugin, the visualization processes flow data to create smooth, proportional connections between employment states across time periods.</p>

<p>Key technical features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Responsive SVG rendering</li>
  <li>Interactive tooltips showing exact percentages</li>
  <li>Hover effects to highlight specific flows</li>
  <li>Gradient definitions for smooth color transitions</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-broader-context">The Broader Context</h2>

<p>This visualization is part of a larger investigation into age-related employment challenges. The data combines insights from multiple sources including ONS statistics, Labour Force Survey data, and research from organizations like Ageing Better and the Resolution Foundation.</p>

<p>The goal isn’t just to present statistics, but to make the human impact of redundancy visible and understandable to policymakers, employers, and the affected individuals themselves.</p>

<h2 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h2>

<p>This Sankey diagram opens up several avenues for further exploration:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Regional variations in outcomes</li>
  <li>Industry-specific transition patterns</li>
  <li>The role of skills in successful transitions</li>
  <li>Interventions that improve outcomes</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m continuing to develop interactive tools that make employment data more accessible and actionable. Each visualization aims to bridge the gap between raw statistics and human understanding.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Interested in commissioning similar visualizations or discussing employment data analysis? <a href="/contact/">Get in touch</a> to explore collaboration opportunities.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="data-visualization" /><category term="employment" /><category term="sankey-diagram" /><category term="d3js" /><category term="career-transitions" /><category term="unemployment" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Exploring the design decisions and data insights behind the interactive Sankey diagram showing employment outcomes for professionals aged 50+ after redundancy.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fixing Universities: A Collective Approach to Financial Crisis</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fixing Universities: A Collective Approach to Financial Crisis" /><published>2025-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/08/01/fixing-universities/"><![CDATA[<p>Universities in the UK are in trouble. Big trouble with pound signs.
Student fees are capped - Unis are paying about £3K a year to teach each student
Research is underfunded. Grants pay only about 70 pence of every research pound. Universities are funding their own research.
The once great bastions of soft power, stricter visa regulations have put off international students.</p>

<p>Let’s start with what won’t work.</p>
<ol>
  <li>The government won’t allow a higher fee cap. There’s no way they would allow the fee to pass the £10,000 ceiling given the state of student debt. It needs to go to £12K. This as been obvious since fees were introduced 15 years ago and immediately all universities charged the maximum allowed fee. No sign of “competition” between universities to teach cheaply. Why? ‘cos teaching is expensive when it involves actual teachers.</li>
  <li>The government won’t increase research spending more than a token amount. Never has happened, never will happen.</li>
  <li>The government won’t lift visa restrictions. The situation for international students will likely get worse rather than better.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="whats-been-tried-the-cutting-paradox">What’s Been Tried: The Cutting Paradox</h2>

<p><strong>Cut costs!</strong> Universities spend a lot on people. All kinds of staff. Cut them! Well, that’s what’s happening. What’s the result? A university that cuts say 500 staff across the board will get a short term benefit of saving the balance sheet for a year or two. It’s always more complicated than you’d think because it’s expensive to get rid of people - it’s a drawn out process that involves paying voluntary severances and compulsory redundancy payments. You may be cutting £30m from your annual budget but you also have to find £10m for all these one off payments. But what are the downsides of that short term balance sheet benefit? You have just made your university smaller. Long term your income is going to go down. You’ve done a sudden shrink in response to (widely predicted) circumstances. You can pretend that “efficiencies” and “productivity boosts” will mean you can do more with fewer staff. But when your staff are already working long hours amidst the threat of compulsory redundancy, how much more productive can you get? Probably LESS productive.</p>

<p>But, say senior managers struggling to get by on six figure salaries, there’s no other way to cut costs. We as a university have done everything we can!</p>

<p>This is a true, as a university you have done everything you can do.</p>

<p>But collectively, as a Universities UK, with 141 member institutions, you have done jack shit.</p>

<h2 id="the-ranking-tables-scam">The Ranking Tables Scam</h2>

<p>To get where we’re going, let’s start with the pointless waste of time and money that are University ranking tables, from eg The Guardian, The Times, The Good University Guide. Every year university PR teams pore over the newly published tables to find a statement that is vaguely accurate and sounds good - “proud to announce we’ve vaulted two places in the guide”, “now the highest rated institution … in north west suffolk”. The truth is that if you ignore the dumb ranks, and look at universities’ average scores over a few years they’re all pretty much the same. Wealthy universities do well, upstart institutions with no money do poorly. The rest are middling. Whisper it: there’s not much difference between them.</p>

<p>For all the money spent on marketing, promoting the unique aspects of the campus, the courses, the people, the buildings, the ethos, etc. Most universities in the UK teach mostly the same courses with the same content.</p>

<p>The problem with universities promoting themselves as unique institutions is that they do everything own their own. (because they’re unique!). Except they aren’t. They are all spending huge sums on the same things - Virtual Learning Environments, Digital Exams, Intranet platforms.</p>

<h2 id="the-15-billion-solution">The £1.5 Billion Solution</h2>

<p>In IT alone, 15% savings could be made by working together. Thats up to £250 million a year across the sector.</p>

<p>Universities claim they can’t do this, and must remain independent, citing competition-law concerns and autonomy. Competition Law is a not a problem. The IT service providers will lobby that it is, but this is where your letters to junior ministers come in.</p>

<p>And autonomy? do me a favour. Whose autonomy? “The university”.
The university should have “autonomy” to choose between say Moodle, Blackboard, Canvas and Brightspace for it’s online learning platform? What you mean is that senior management and a special working group wants autonomy. They want to flex their bulging senior management muscles. But for every single person who would actually use the system - the lectures putting crap on it, and the students using it - there is no autonomy at all. They have to use the system they’re provided.</p>

<p>It’s yet another example of the outdated and inefficient management structure of universities costing them millions.</p>

<p>And universities already use collective procurement through UK Universities Purchasing Consortia (UKPC), and other regional bodies. This currently saves about £500 million a year. Nice. but with full nationwide collective procurement, this could be tripled to about £1.5 billion per year. Which would be even nicer.</p>

<h2 id="a-case-study-ethics-systems">A Case Study: Ethics Systems</h2>

<p>Let’s look at a case study. Most universities in the UK use Infonetica Ethics RM for processing ethics applications for research with human participants. Most people who use these systems don’t know that because each university has a separate contract with Infonetica and brands their internal version with their own stupid name for it. It’s a generally slow and clunky system, but that’s common for IT in the education sector. As anyone who has ever applied for ethical approval on this system is only too well aware, it takes hours to figure out what do to and how to complete the online forms in a way that won’t result in multiple length rejections. And as anyone who has ever reviewed ethics applications submitted this way knows only too well, it takes far too long to review each problem and highlight the inconsistencies with uni policy.</p>

<p>This is for many reasons, usually related to the decisions originally made when the uni set up the system with Infonetica many years ago, and the complete lack of useful documentation. Fixing systems with bad UI and bad documentation is slow and expensive. So unis don’t do it. But if the same system is used across more than a 100 universities, each uni’s contribution to fixing the problem is now only 1% of the time and cost. It’s practically free.</p>

<h2 id="shared-teaching-materials">Shared Teaching Materials</h2>

<p>But I would go further than that. Above I noted that most university courses are the same. Does it matter where you study psychology, or mechanical engineering or history? Especially where there is an oversight body (eg the BPS for psychology), there are great similarities, let’s put it that way. so it’s perplexing why individual lecturers spend so many hundreds of hours duplicating the efforts of hundreds of other lecturers replicating similar teaching materials (slides, videos, handouts, worksheets) and assessments (exams, essays, mcqs etc). Modify a shared core, people. Saves time and money.</p>

<p>With all these savings, even in the current crisis in UK HE, there would have been no need for compulsory redundancies. None at all.</p>

<p>It’s too late to save me. But I’d like to think that lessons could be learned. Go out there and make this happen, people!</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-finance" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="funding-crisis" /><category term="collective-procurement" /><category term="shared-services" /><category term="education-policy" /><category term="institutional-efficiency" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Universities in the UK are in financial trouble. Instead of individual cost-cutting that shrinks institutions, the sector could save billions through collective action and smarter revenue diversification.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Finance" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Finance" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beating The Odds: Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beating The Odds: Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo" /><published>2025-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/31/beating-the-odds/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" alt="Professional looking person with graphs and career pathway charts in background" /></p>

<h2 id="four-months-in-mid-life-employment-limbo">Four Months in Mid-Life Employment Limbo</h2>

<p>I was made redundant 4 months ago today.</p>

<p><strong>31 March:</strong> I executed the traditional farewell ritual of the mid-career professional: an almost-imperceptible shrug in the general direction of the photocopier and a short walk to the car park. No speeches, no novelty cake, not even a limp balloon. Just me, a cardboard box and the sort of existential soundtrack you normally get in French cinema.</p>

<p><strong>1 April:</strong> New month, new life. I was up with the larks, pounding the cross-trainer in a heroic attempt to sculpt a “new me”. Resistance machines were conquered, endorphins flowed, and—for a glorious forty-eight hours—I was basically the poster child for Mid-Life Reinvention.</p>

<p><strong>3 April:</strong> Doughnuts happened. Then ice cream. If Ben &amp; Jerry ever need to boost quarterly sales, they should simply make more fifty-somethings redundant; we’ll do the heavy lifting.</p>

<p>Fast-forward four months: zero salary, zero job, and—rather paradoxically—a very busy diary. I’ve uploaded a few LinkedIn posts and articles, but that’s the tip of the iceberg. It turns out that finding work in 2025 is very different from the last time I was in the job market. That was when Mark Zuckerberg was still in high school, Elon Musk had yet to be fired from PayPal, and Google was a long way from becoming a verb.</p>

<p>So what’s it actually like, drifting through middle-age employment limbo with a gym membership you no longer use and a freezer full of salted-caramel regret?</p>

<p><strong>It’s actually not too bad, apart from the whole zero salary thing.</strong></p>

<h2 id="the-numbers-game">The Numbers Game</h2>

<p>And I’m not alone. Exiting a professional job in your fifties (unwillingly) is not a rare occurrence, especially in 2025.</p>

<p>To figure out what happens next, I turned not to necromancy or tarot cards but to statistics and data visualisation. I’ve done a little research, the sources for which you’ll find at the end of this article. There isn’t a single definitive source of data so I’ve extracted some figures and done some careful extrapolation. And guesswork.</p>

<iframe src="/sankey.html" width="100%" height="600" frameborder="0" style="border: 1px solid #ddd; border-radius: 8px; margin: 20px 0;"></iframe>

<h3 id="figure-1-career-pathways-after-redundancy-at-50">Figure 1. Career Pathways After Redundancy at 50+</h3>

<p>Should I be worried that after 4 months I don’t have a job - any job? Not really. Only <strong>14% of my age group have another professional job within 3 months</strong> of leaving the old one. Another 14% are in lower paid work, and 7% say they’re “self-employed”, but <strong>two thirds are still jobless</strong>.</p>

<p>This jobless figure does drop and two years after redundancy only 20% are unemployed, although long term this goes up to nearly a third.</p>

<p>Should I be concerned that the odds are against me: I have a <strong>less than evens chance</strong> of landing in a professional job sometime in the next few years?</p>

<h2 id="understanding-the-odds">Understanding the Odds</h2>

<p>Some people resist any discussion of probability, preferring an unexamined optimism that screens out unfavourable statistics. I take the opposite view: the more granular the data—baseline rates, confidence intervals, omitted caveats—the better. Equipped with that information, we can assess alternatives rationally rather than intuitively.</p>

<p>For me, this is what it means to <strong>beat the odds</strong>. It is not a matter of willing a coin to land heads or expecting double-sixes on demand; it is a systematic appraisal of the distribution of outcomes under different courses of action and an informed adjustment of strategy in light of those probabilities.</p>

<p><strong>Chance remains a constant, but its impact can be moderated when we understand, rather than ignore, the numbers.</strong></p>

<p>There’s much more to say about what these figures tell us, but even I know that an article full of numbers should be brief.</p>

<h2 id="your-turn">Your Turn</h2>

<p>How did your own post-redundancy odds play out? Drop a note below—stats or stories equally welcome.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="sources">Sources</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <table>
      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td>Centre for Ageing Better, Work</td>
          <td>State of Ageing in 2020 – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/work-state-ageing-2020">ageing-better.org.uk/work-state-ageing-2020</a></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </table>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Resolution Foundation, A U-shaped crisis: the impact of the COVID-19 crisis on older workers – <a href="https://www.resolutionfoundation.org/publications/a-u-shaped-crisis/">resolutionfoundation.org/publications/a-u-shaped-crisis</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Resolution Foundation, “COVID-19 crisis has caused the biggest annual employment fall for older workers since the 1980s” – <a href="https://www.resolutionfoundation.org/press-releases/covid-19-crisis-has-caused-the-biggest-annual-employment-fall-for-older-workers-since-the-1980s/">resolutionfoundation.org/press-releases</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Guardian, “Over-50s who lose jobs much more likely to stay unemployed, study finds” – <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/2021/jan/18/over-50s-who-lose-jobs-much-more-likely-to-stay-unemployed-study-finds">theguardian.com/society/2021/jan/18</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Rest Less, “Redundancies Amongst the Over 50s Have Nearly Tripled in a Year” – <a href="https://wiseage.org.uk/2021/04/redundancies-amongst-the-over-50s-have-nearly-tripled-in-a-year/">wiseage.org.uk/2021/04</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Centre for Ageing Better, Redundancy support for Over 50s – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/redundancy-support-over-50s">ageing-better.org.uk/redundancy-support-over-50s</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Office for National Statistics, Analysis of Job Changers and Stayers – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts/uksectoraccounts/compendium/economicreview/april2019/analysisofjobchangersandstayers">ons.gov.uk/economy/nationalaccounts</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Centre for Ageing Better, The State of Ageing 2022 – <a href="https://ageing-better.org.uk/state-of-ageing">ageing-better.org.uk/state-of-ageing</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Office for National Statistics, Dataset RED02: Redundancies by age, industry and region – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peoplenotinwork/redundancies/datasets/redundanciesbyindustryagesexandreemploymentratesred02">ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket</a></p>
  </li>
  <li>Office for National Statistics, Employment in the UK: July 2025 bulletin – <a href="https://www.ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket/peopleinwork/employmentandemployeetypes/bulletins/employmentintheuk/july2025">ons.gov.uk/employmentandlabourmarket</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="employment" /><category term="career" /><category term="redundancy" /><category term="job-search" /><category term="over-50s" /><category term="unemployment" /><category term="career-transition" /><category term="employment-statistics" /><category term="professional-development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I was made redundant 4 months ago today. Fast-forward four months: zero salary, zero job, and—rather paradoxically—a very busy diary. So what's it actually like, drifting through middle-age employment limbo with a gym membership you no longer use and a freezer full of salted-caramel regret?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-31-beating-the-odds/career-odds.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Murder a University: A Guide to Institutional Death</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Murder a University: A Guide to Institutional Death" /><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/30/how-to-murder-a-university/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent posts I’ve already skipped indelicately through Britain’s higher-education money-pit, tutted at missed savings, and poked the soggy bits of management. “Cheer up,” I promised. So naturally it’s time to talk about death. Not yours, happily, but the demise of an entire university – a topic so bleak it makes actuarial tables look frisky.</p>

<h2 id="the-impossible-dream-of-university-death">The Impossible Dream of University Death</h2>

<p>Universities are remarkably difficult to kill. Unlike your corner shop or local restaurant, they cannot simply lock the doors and disappear into the night. They are typically incorporated as charitable entities with Royal Charters or established under specific legislation, making them about as easy to dissolve as the House of Lords (and roughly as likely to happen).</p>

<h2 id="the-office-for-students-university-undertaker">The Office for Students: University Undertaker</h2>

<p>When a university starts circling the financial drain, the Office for Students (OfS) swoops in like a particularly bureaucratic grim reaper. Their powers include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Financial monitoring:</strong> Think of it as a fiscal heart monitor, beeping increasingly urgently</li>
  <li><strong>Intervention orders:</strong> Forcing universities to accept external governance</li>
  <li><strong>Student protection:</strong> Ensuring current students can complete their studies elsewhere</li>
  <li><strong>Revocation of degree-awarding powers:</strong> The academic equivalent of cardiac arrest</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-legal-labyrinth">The Legal Labyrinth</h2>

<p>Closing a university involves navigating a maze of regulations that would make Kafka weep:</p>

<p><strong>Student Protection Plans:</strong> Every university must have a plan for what happens to students if the institution fails. It’s like a will for academic programs.</p>

<p><strong>Asset Distribution:</strong> University assets cannot be sold for private profit—they must be transferred to other charitable or educational purposes.</p>

<p><strong>Staff and Pension Obligations:</strong> Universities cannot simply abandon employment contracts or pension commitments.</p>

<p><strong>Research Continuity:</strong> Ongoing research projects must be preserved or transferred, along with their ethical approvals and data.</p>

<h2 id="case-studies-in-institutional-mortality">Case Studies in Institutional Mortality</h2>

<p><strong>The University of Wales:</strong> Not technically dead, but so diminished it’s essentially academic roadkill. Once a federal university overseeing multiple institutions, it’s now reduced to validating degrees for overseas partners.</p>

<p><strong>London Metropolitan University:</strong> Nearly died in 2012 when it lost its license to sponsor international students. Survived, but only after dramatic restructuring and significant downsizing.</p>

<h2 id="the-zombie-university-scenario">The Zombie University Scenario</h2>

<p>The most likely outcome for failing universities isn’t death but zombification: institutions that continue to exist but have lost their essential functions. They limp along with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Dramatically reduced course offerings</li>
  <li>Skeleton staff</li>
  <li>Crumbling infrastructure</li>
  <li>Diminished research capacity</li>
  <li>Reputation in free fall</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="financial-rigor-mortis">Financial Rigor Mortis</h2>

<p>Universities experience financial death in stages:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Cash flow problems:</strong> Late payment of bills, delayed salaries</li>
  <li><strong>Credit downgrades:</strong> Banks start demanding higher interest rates</li>
  <li><strong>Regulatory intervention:</strong> OfS imposes external oversight</li>
  <li><strong>Student recruitment collapse:</strong> Nobody wants to enroll at a failing institution</li>
  <li><strong>Staff exodus:</strong> Academics flee to more stable institutions</li>
  <li><strong>Academic rigor mortis:</strong> The institution cannot fulfill its core functions</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-political-dimension">The Political Dimension</h2>

<p>No government wants to be responsible for closing universities, especially ones with significant local economic impact. This political reality means that failing institutions often receive:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Emergency loans</li>
  <li>Merger opportunities with stronger partners</li>
  <li>Gradual managed decline rather than sudden closure</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="prevention-better-than-cure">Prevention Better Than Cure</h2>

<p>The best way to avoid institutional death is early intervention:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Realistic financial planning:</strong> Based on actual revenue, not wishful thinking</li>
  <li><strong>Diversified income streams:</strong> Not relying solely on tuition fees</li>
  <li><strong>Strategic partnerships:</strong> Sharing costs and risks with other institutions</li>
  <li><strong>Regular health checks:</strong> Financial monitoring before crisis hits</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion-the-undead-academy">Conclusion: The Undead Academy</h2>

<p>In practice, university “death” is more often a transformation into something unrecognizable than actual closure. The institution may survive, but its soul—the ability to provide quality education and research—may be long gone.</p>

<p>Perhaps the real question isn’t how to kill a university, but how to keep it truly alive. In an era of financial pressure and political interference, that might be the greater challenge.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-governance" /><category term="insolvency" /><category term="university-closure" /><category term="OfS-regulation" /><category term="insolvency-law" /><category term="student-protection" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="institutional-failure" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A UK university cannot simply press CTRL-ALT-DELETE and vanish. Here's what actually happens when institutions reach the end of the financial road.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Closure" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Closure" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond the Balance Sheet: Why UK Universities Need a Busyness Model</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond the Balance Sheet: Why UK Universities Need a Busyness Model" /><published>2025-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/28/beyond-the-balance-sheet/"><![CDATA[<p>Calling a university’s strategy its “business model” is a bit like calling the Royal Opera House a karaoke bar— both involve singing for money, but that’s where the resemblance ends. Yes, the UK sector’s fiscal plumbing is hissing ominously, but the ‘business model’ mantra pares back a sprawling public-good ecosystem until it resembles someone trying to fund science with a primary-school bake sale.</p>

<h2 id="the-problem-with-business-models">The Problem with Business Models</h2>

<p>Business models are designed to maximize shareholder value through efficient resource allocation and competitive advantage. Universities, by contrast, are charitable institutions designed to maximize public benefit through education, research, and knowledge transfer.</p>

<p>Trying to apply business model thinking to universities creates several problems:</p>

<p><strong>Short-term vs. Long-term Thinking:</strong> Businesses optimize for quarterly results; universities should optimize for generational impact.</p>

<p><strong>Measurable vs. Immeasurable Value:</strong> Business success is measured in profit margins; university success includes cultural preservation, scientific breakthrough, and social mobility.</p>

<p><strong>Competition vs. Collaboration:</strong> Business models assume zero-sum competition; universities create positive-sum knowledge that benefits everyone.</p>

<h2 id="enter-the-busyness-model">Enter the Busyness Model</h2>

<p>Instead of business models, universities need “busyness models”—frameworks that capture how they create value through being busy with meaningful work rather than just profitable work.</p>

<p>A busyness model would measure:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Research Impact:</strong> Not just publication counts, but real-world application</li>
  <li><strong>Educational Value:</strong> Not just graduate employment rates, but lifetime learning outcomes</li>
  <li><strong>Social Return:</strong> Not just economic contribution, but community development</li>
  <li><strong>Knowledge Exchange:</strong> Not just technology transfer, but cultural and intellectual enrichment</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-multiple-value-problem">The Multiple Value Problem</h2>

<p>Universities create multiple types of value simultaneously:</p>

<p><strong>Economic Value:</strong> Skilled graduates, research commercialization, local economic impact</p>

<p><strong>Social Value:</strong> Cultural preservation, social mobility, civic engagement</p>

<p><strong>Intellectual Value:</strong> New knowledge, critical thinking, artistic creation</p>

<p><strong>Long-term Value:</strong> Institutional memory, intergenerational knowledge transfer</p>

<p>Trying to reduce this to a simple business model is like trying to measure a symphony with a profit-and-loss statement.</p>

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h2>

<p>The business model obsession leads to:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Cutting “unprofitable” subjects like philosophy and languages</li>
  <li>Prioritizing revenue-generating activities over educational quality</li>
  <li>Treating students as customers rather than scholars</li>
  <li>Focusing on measurable outcomes rather than transformational education</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="a-different-approach-social-return-on-investment">A Different Approach: Social Return on Investment</h2>

<p>Instead of business models, universities could use Social Return on Investment (SROI) frameworks that capture:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Direct Benefits:</strong> Graduate earnings, research commercialization</li>
  <li><strong>Indirect Benefits:</strong> Community development, cultural enrichment</li>
  <li><strong>Induced Benefits:</strong> Long-term societal transformation through education</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-ecosystem-perspective">The Ecosystem Perspective</h2>

<p>Universities exist within knowledge ecosystems, not business markets. They:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Share knowledge freely rather than hoarding competitive advantage</li>
  <li>Collaborate with institutions that might be considered “competitors”</li>
  <li>Create public goods that benefit society beyond their immediate stakeholders</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="international-examples">International Examples</h2>

<p><strong>Finland:</strong> Universities are funded based on broader societal outcomes, not just economic metrics.</p>

<p><strong>Germany:</strong> The dual system combines practical training with theoretical education, recognizing multiple forms of value.</p>

<p><strong>Canada:</strong> Provincial funding models incorporate community development and indigenous knowledge preservation.</p>

<h2 id="practical-steps">Practical Steps</h2>

<p>Universities could develop better busyness models by:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Measuring Social Impact:</strong> Tracking graduates’ civic engagement, not just employment</li>
  <li><strong>Valuing Knowledge Commons:</strong> Recognizing open research and public engagement</li>
  <li><strong>Community Integration:</strong> Measuring local economic and cultural development</li>
  <li><strong>Long-term Thinking:</strong> Planning for generational rather than annual outcomes</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="conclusion-beyond-the-bottom-line">Conclusion: Beyond the Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Universities are not businesses, and trying to make them behave like businesses destroys their essential public value. Instead of business models, they need busyness models that capture the full scope of their societal contribution.</p>

<p>The goal should not be to run universities like businesses, but to run them like the complex, valuable public institutions they are. That requires different metrics, different timeframes, and different definitions of success.</p>

<p>After all, the best universities have never been about efficiency—they’ve been about effectiveness at transforming both individuals and society. That’s a kind of busyness worth investing in.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-strategy" /><category term="public-value" /><category term="university-business-model" /><category term="SROI" /><category term="social-return-investment" /><category term="public-good" /><category term="UK-universities" /><category term="university-finance" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Calling a university's strategy its 'business model' is like calling the Royal Opera House a karaoke bar. Universities need a busyness model focused on public value, not just profit margins.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Strategy" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Strategy" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Governmental Shrugs: When Car Factories Matter More Than Universities</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/25/governmental-shrugs/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Governmental Shrugs: When Car Factories Matter More Than Universities" /><published>2025-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-25T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/25/governmental-shrugs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/25/governmental-shrugs/"><![CDATA[<p>At British universities, 2025 is shaping up to be the year when 10,000 academic, technical and professional posts toddle off towards the Jobcentre, waving their P45s like tear-stained handkerchiefs. Westminster’s response has been a philosophical shrug tucked inside the well-rehearsed line that universities are “independent organisations” that really ought to jolly well clean up their own mess. By contrast, the merest newspaper flutter suggesting Lotus might moth-ball its Norfolk factory (all 1,300 jobs of it) prompted the Business Secretary to speed-dial the Chinese owners, after which the company dutifully announced that of course it wasn’t going anywhere, thank you very much. Apparently some independent organisations are more independent than others.</p>

<h2 id="a-crisis-in-ten-thousand-lessons">A Crisis in Ten Thousand Lessons</h2>

<p>Teaching an undergraduate now costs about <strong>£12,500 a head</strong>, yet the fee cap in England has been frozen at <strong>£9,250 since 2017</strong>. Even Labour’s promised bump to a grandiose £9,535 next year adds little more than garnish. Unsurprisingly, the Office for Students reckons most institutions will be running deficits within two years.</p>

<p>Research is no lifeboat either: UK Research &amp; Innovation normally pays <strong>80% of full economic cost</strong>, leaving universities to find the other 20% down the back of the sofa. Across the sector, only <strong>71% of research costs are actually recovered</strong>.</p>

<p>And then we removed the only profitable revenue stream. A ban on most dependants from January 2024 helped push international student visa applications down <strong>12% in a single year</strong>, while dependant visas collapsed by <strong>83%</strong>. When even The Pie News has the words “record fall” in its headline, you know it’s not a vintage year for campus optimism.</p>

<h2 id="government-guidance-please-keep-calm-and-self-fund">Government Guidance: Please Keep Calm and Self-Fund</h2>

<p>Asked what might be done, ministers reliably point out that universities are free, sovereign entities, presumably able to mint their own bullion and grow money trees next to the sociology building. There are, of course, the odd exceptions north of Hadrian’s Wall: Dundee secured a £62 million Scottish Government loan (pronounced in Edinburgh as “fiscal prudence”, in St Andrews as “cheque-book socialism”). But for everyone else, the official line resembles a Victorian medical pamphlet: <em>keep warm, drink beef tea, and try not to fade away</em>.</p>

<h2 id="meanwhile-in-norfolk-deploy-the-panic-button">Meanwhile in Norfolk: Deploy the Panic-Button</h2>

<p>When a Financial Times whisper suggested Lotus might slide its production over to the United States, Whitehall’s hazard lights came on. Within hours the Business Secretary was arranging urgent talks, Lotus confirmed Hethel was safe for now, and Norfolk exhaled. The jobs at risk? A mere <strong>1,300</strong>—roughly the headcount of a mid-sized faculty at, say, Sussex, but clearly of far greater strategic significance.</p>

<p>To be fair, car making is one of the few industrial pastimes Britain still practises competitively. Even in a wobbly 2024 the nation built almost <strong>780,000 cars</strong>, exporting over three-quarters of them, and Whitehall is understandably twitchy about losing any remaining assembly lines. A fresh UK–US trade tweak trimming tariffs has only heightened the sense that the sector is a precious, if precarious, jewel.</p>

<h2 id="spot-the-difference-clue-it-isnt-the-extra-zero">Spot the Difference (Clue: It Isn’t the Extra Zero)</h2>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Sector</th>
      <th>Jobs under threat</th>
      <th>Typical government reflex</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Universities</td>
      <td><strong>10,000</strong></td>
      <td><em>“They’re independent; pass the biscuits.”</em></td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lotus Cars</td>
      <td><strong>1,300</strong></td>
      <td>Phone call, statement, comfort blanket</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The delightfully lopsided enthusiasm suggests that, in the national pecking order, a hand-built sports car outranks a biomedical lab, a languages department and the entire postgraduate research pipeline combined. It may also explain why some vice-chancellors are eyeing the idea of bolting spoilers to the admin block and rebranding as “Higher Education, but with Cup Holders”.</p>

<h2 id="why-it-matters-beyond-the-ivory-tower">Why It Matters (Beyond the Ivory Tower)</h2>

<p>Universities underpin £95 billion of economic output, drive half of all basic research and train the very engineers Lotus will need for its next electric model. Starve them, and the future supply of skilled workers, patents and—let’s be honest—pub quiz champions goes with them. Yet policy continues to treat the sector as a cost centre rather than the soft-power and productivity machine every industrial strategy paper claims to cherish.</p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts-a-polite-suggestion">Closing Thoughts: A Polite Suggestion</h2>

<p>If 10,000 university jobs do vanish this year, imagine the ministerial switchboard lit up with as many calls as Norfolk enjoyed last weekend. Until then, campus leaders might consider relocating to a disused airfield, painting everything British-Racing-Green and applying for a small but tasteful government rescue package. Stranger things have certainly received a ministerial phone-call.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="government-policy" /><category term="economic-priorities" /><category term="university-funding" /><category term="job-losses" /><category term="government-response" /><category term="economic-policy" /><category term="UK-priorities" /><category term="car-industry" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Westminster rushes to save 1,300 car jobs at Lotus but shrugs at 10,000 university redundancies. Apparently some independent organisations are more independent than others.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=Government+Policy" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=Government+Policy" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Ethics in Artificial Intelligence: Yes, There Is a Problem</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/23/ethics-in-artificial-intelligence/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ethics in Artificial Intelligence: Yes, There Is a Problem" /><published>2025-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-23T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/23/ethics-in-artificial-intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/23/ethics-in-artificial-intelligence/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/images/posts/2025-07-23-ethics-in-artificial-intelligence/ai-ethics.jpg" alt="Abstract visualization of AI neural networks with ethical scales and human silhouettes" /></p>

<h2 id="a-clear-and-candid-guide-to-ai-ethics">A Clear and Candid Guide to AI Ethics</h2>

<p>Artificial intelligence (AI) has catapulted from the plaything of graduate students to the digital weather system that now soaks every corner of the economy. The upsides are dazzling; the downsides, well, they’re the reason you’re reading this article instead of a holiday brochure.</p>

<p>This paper peers—torch in hand—into the trickier nooks of AI from a global vantage point. We’ll rummage through its resource guzzling, copyright snacking, bias-soaked data diet, the Silicon Valley swagger that births it, and the many honourable (and not-so-honourable) uses already on parade.</p>

<h2 id="energy-and-human-resource-consumption">Energy and Human Resource Consumption</h2>

<h3 id="the-environmental-footprint-of-ai">The Environmental Footprint of AI</h3>

<p>Training large AI models requires enormous computational power, translating into heavy energy usage and a substantial carbon footprint. For example, the training of OpenAI’s GPT-3 model is estimated to have consumed <strong>1,287 MWh of electricity</strong>, emitting over <strong>550 metric tons of CO₂</strong> – on par with hundreds of transatlantic flights<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. This process also used more than 700,000 liters of water for cooling data centre servers<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Globally, data centres (which host AI workloads among other tasks) account for about <strong>1.5% of electricity consumption</strong> (around 415 TWh in 2024), a share expected to roughly double by 2030 due to AI growth<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup><sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>. In practical terms, that means data centres could soon draw nearly 945 TWh annually – about as much power as the entire country of Japan uses in a year<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Major tech hubs like the US, Europe and China currently consume 85% of data centre energy<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup><sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>, highlighting a global disparity. Even after models are trained, the energy for running AI (“inference”) at scale can eclipse training costs – one study noted that inference could comprise 90% of an AI model’s total energy lifecycle as millions of users prompt these models daily<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="the-human-labour-behind-automated-ai">The Human Labour Behind “Automated” AI</h3>

<p>Less visible but equally critical is the human labour powering AI development. Behind every “smart” AI system are often thousands of human workers who label data, moderate content, and train AI models – tasks that can be repetitive, grueling, or psychologically taxing.</p>

<p>In 2021, OpenAI quietly outsourced the job of filtering toxic and harmful content (to make ChatGPT safer) to contractors in Kenya, <strong>paying them less than $2 per hour</strong>. These workers had to read and label tens of thousands of disturbing text snippets – including descriptions of child sexual abuse, torture, and violence – so that the AI could learn to recognise and avoid producing such content<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The psychological toll was enormous: moderators reported trauma, anxiety and lasting mental health damage from constant exposure to graphic material<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup><sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup>. Several have since filed petitions and lawsuits (for instance, in Kenya) over exploitative conditions – citing low pay (around $1.50–$3 an hour), inadequate counseling support, and even abrupt dismissals after the projects ended<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup><sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup>.</p>

<p>This “ghost work” underpins not just ChatGPT but many AI services – from social media moderation to self-driving car vision – often outsourced to developing countries where labour is cheap.</p>

<h2 id="copyright-and-creator-rights">Copyright and Creator Rights</h2>

<p>AI’s voracious appetite for data has it nibbling at every creative buffet—books, art, code, music—often without so much as a “may I?”. Contemporary AI models learn from vast datasets scraped from the internet – encompassing books, articles, code, images, music and more – much of which is copyrighted material obtained without explicit consent from the authors or artists.</p>

<h3 id="unconsented-training-data">Unconsented Training Data</h3>

<p>Writers, visual artists, musicians and other creators have grown alarmed at AI models being trained on their work. In mid-2023, a group of prominent authors – including <strong>Michael Chabon, Jodi Picoult and George R.R. Martin</strong> – sued OpenAI, alleging that their novels and essays were used to train ChatGPT without consent<sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup><sup id="fnref:15"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup>.</p>

<p>They pointed out that the chatbot could accurately summarise their books or imitate their writing styles, implying it had effectively ingested and learned from their copyrighted texts<sup id="fnref:16"><a href="#fn:16" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">16</a></sup>. This lawsuit is one of several class actions by authors and publishers against AI firms, and it followed similar cases by visual artists against generative AI image companies<sup id="fnref:17"><a href="#fn:17" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">17</a></sup><sup id="fnref:18"><a href="#fn:18" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">18</a></sup>.</p>

<p>In a landmark example, a class-action suit <strong>Andersen v. Stability AI</strong> was filed in 2023 by a group of artists after they discovered the AI image generator Stable Diffusion had been trained on 5 billion images scraped from the web (LAION dataset), including their own artworks, without any permission<sup id="fnref:19"><a href="#fn:19" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">19</a></sup><sup id="fnref:20"><a href="#fn:20" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">20</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="legal-and-ethical-tensions">Legal and Ethical Tensions</h3>

<p>Legally, the question of whether using copyrighted data for AI training is “fair use” or infringement is still being decided. In a February 2025 decision, a U.S. court (<strong>Thomson Reuters v. ROSS</strong>) held that wholesale copying of a competitor’s copyrighted material (legal case summaries from Westlaw) to train an AI research tool was not fair use<sup id="fnref:21"><a href="#fn:21" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">21</a></sup><sup id="fnref:22"><a href="#fn:22" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">22</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The judge noted that the AI in that case wasn’t even a generative model, but a search tool that repackaged the original texts, directly harming the copyright owner’s market<sup id="fnref:23"><a href="#fn:23" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">23</a></sup><sup id="fnref:24"><a href="#fn:24" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">24</a></sup>. While generative AI may muddy the waters (since outputs aren’t verbatim copies, but can be derivative in style or content), the legal trend suggests courts are wary of unfettered, unlicensed use of copyrighted datasets.</p>

<h3 id="toward-solutions--consent-and-transparency">Toward Solutions – Consent and Transparency</h3>

<p>Policymakers are starting to respond. The draft <strong>EU AI Act</strong> includes provisions that AI developers must disclose any copyrighted material used in training their models<sup id="fnref:25"><a href="#fn:25" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">25</a></sup><sup id="fnref:26"><a href="#fn:26" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">26</a></sup>. European lawmakers explicitly added a requirement that generative AI systems like ChatGPT publish summaries of the copyrighted data they were trained on, aiming to introduce transparency and enable rightsholders to claim misuse<sup id="fnref:27"><a href="#fn:27" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">27</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="training-data-and-bias">Training Data and Bias</h2>

<p>The ancient maxim “garbage in, garbage out” gets a silicon makeover here. Feed an AI dodgy data and you’ll get dodgy decisions—only faster and at scale.</p>

<h3 id="opaque-datasets-and-hidden-biases">Opaque Datasets and Hidden Biases</h3>

<p>Many advanced AI models are trained on colossal datasets that are not fully disclosed to the public or regulators. For instance, when OpenAI released GPT-4 in 2023, it notably provided <strong>no details</strong> about the model’s architecture, training methods, or dataset composition, citing competition and safety concerns<sup id="fnref:28"><a href="#fn:28" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">28</a></sup><sup id="fnref:29"><a href="#fn:29" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">29</a></sup>.</p>

<p>While trade secrecy is understandable, this opacity has a direct ethical impact: without knowing what data an AI was trained on, it’s “impossible to evaluate” what biases or blind spots might be built into it<sup id="fnref:30"><a href="#fn:30" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">30</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="bias-in-bias-out--examples">Bias in, Bias Out – Examples</h3>

<p>When biased data goes in, discriminatory outcomes come out. A notorious example was <strong>Amazon’s AI recruiting tool</strong>, an algorithm developed to screen resumes. It was trained on ten years of past hiring data – which were skewed toward male candidates (reflecting the tech industry’s male dominance)<sup id="fnref:31"><a href="#fn:31" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">31</a></sup><sup id="fnref:32"><a href="#fn:32" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">32</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The AI “taught itself” that male applicants were preferable and began penalising resumes that mentioned “women’s” (as in “women’s chess club”), and downgrading graduates of women’s colleges<sup id="fnref:33"><a href="#fn:33" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">33</a></sup><sup id="fnref:34"><a href="#fn:34" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">34</a></sup>. In effect, the system became sexist, systematically filtering out qualified women. Amazon’s engineers tried to correct the specific flags, but they couldn’t guarantee the AI wouldn’t find new ways to discriminate, so the project was eventually scrapped<sup id="fnref:35"><a href="#fn:35" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">35</a></sup><sup id="fnref:36"><a href="#fn:36" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">36</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Another well-documented case is in criminal justice: risk assessment algorithms used by courts to predict reoffending have exhibited racial bias. ProPublica’s famous 2016 investigation into the <strong>COMPAS system</strong> found that black defendants were falsely labeled “high risk” at nearly twice the rate of white defendants, while white defendants were more frequently mislabeled as low risk<sup id="fnref:37"><a href="#fn:37" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">37</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="the-silicon-valley-ethos-and-the-drive-to-innovate">The Silicon Valley Ethos and the Drive to Innovate</h2>

<p>Silicon Valley’s original mantra—”move fast and break things”—is all fun and games until the “things” include society.</p>

<h3 id="from-motto-to-liability">From Motto to Liability</h3>

<p>In the startup heyday, “move fast and break things” was celebrated as a recipe for disrupting incumbents and achieving technological leaps. However, when it comes to AI systems that can affect millions of lives, this approach can be dangerously reckless. A recent poll found that <strong>72% of Americans prefer AI development to slow down</strong> with more guardrails, versus only 8% who want it to speed up<sup id="fnref:38"><a href="#fn:38" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">38</a></sup><sup id="fnref:39"><a href="#fn:39" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">39</a></sup>.</p>

<p>High-profile mishaps have validated these fears: from chatbots that went awry spouting misinformation or hate, to social networks unleashing algorithms that amplified societal divisions. The “launch now, fix later” mentality is being increasingly questioned.</p>

<h3 id="profit-driven-innovation-and-moral-hazard">Profit-Driven Innovation and Moral Hazard</h3>

<p>Silicon Valley’s ecosystem runs on venture capital and the promise of massive profits. This can incentivise a single-minded focus on growth metrics and market capture, potentially overshadowing ethical considerations. AI has become a competitive arms race among tech giants and startups, with enormous financial stakes – which can lead to corners being cut.</p>

<p>Gary Marcus observed a “moral descent” in Big Tech: as companies grew more powerful and profitable, “the desire to do good decreases… in the quest for growth”<sup id="fnref:40"><a href="#fn:40" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">40</a></sup>. He argues that many firms talk about altruistic missions, but in recent years have prioritised profit maximisation at the expense of users and society<sup id="fnref:41"><a href="#fn:41" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">41</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="uses-and-misuses-of-ai">Uses and Misuses of AI</h2>

<p>AI is a dual-use tool: the same algorithms that power beneficial applications can be misappropriated for malicious or harmful ends.</p>

<h3 id="ai-in-social-media-deepfakes-and-algorithmic-amplification">AI in Social Media: Deepfakes and Algorithmic Amplification</h3>

<h4 id="deepfakes-and-misinformation">Deepfakes and Misinformation</h4>

<p>Deepfakes are hyper-realistic fake videos or audio generated by AI, often depicting someone saying or doing things they never did. In the wrong hands, deepfakes can be a potent weapon for misinformation, political propaganda, or personal harassment.</p>

<p>A striking statistic: an analysis in 2023 found that <strong>98% of deepfake videos online were pornographic</strong>, targeting women in 99% of cases<sup id="fnref:42"><a href="#fn:42" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">42</a></sup>. In other words, the vast majority of deepfakes globally consist of non-consensual sexual images – typically a woman’s face superimposed on explicit content – effectively a high-tech form of revenge porn or voyeurism.</p>

<h4 id="algorithmic-amplification-of-harmful-content">Algorithmic Amplification of Harmful Content</h4>

<p>Social media algorithms – the content recommendation AIs on Facebook, YouTube, TikTok, etc. – determine what billions of people see in their feeds. Their optimisation for engagement can lead to the amplification of extreme or harmful content, creating echo chambers and fueling polarisation.</p>

<p>Facebook’s own algorithm changes were found to preferentially boost content that sparked anger or intense reactions, which tended to be divisive posts or misinformation, thus contributing to a more toxic discourse<sup id="fnref:43"><a href="#fn:43" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">43</a></sup><sup id="fnref:44"><a href="#fn:44" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">44</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="fraud-and-scams-voice-cloning-and-phishing-automation">Fraud and Scams: Voice Cloning and Phishing Automation</h3>

<h4 id="voice-cloning-and-imposter-scams">Voice Cloning and “Imposter” Scams</h4>

<p>Scammers have begun exploiting trust by using AI to clone voices from just a short recording. In one chilling case, an Arizona mother received a call that mimicked her 15-year-old daughter’s voice perfectly, sobbing that she’d been kidnapped and begging for help<sup id="fnref:45"><a href="#fn:45" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">45</a></sup><sup id="fnref:46"><a href="#fn:46" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">46</a></sup>. The voice and cries were so convincing that the mother was certain it was her child – the scammers demanded a ransom, threatening violence. It turned out the daughter was safe; the entire call was a hoax using an AI-generated voice.</p>

<p>A survey by security firm McAfee found <strong>70% of people said they might not distinguish a cloned voice from the real thing</strong>, and alarmingly, today’s AI needs only about <strong>3 seconds of audio sample</strong> to reproduce a person’s voice with high fidelity<sup id="fnref:47"><a href="#fn:47" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">47</a></sup>.</p>

<h4 id="ai-generated-phishing-and-fraudulent-content">AI-Generated Phishing and Fraudulent Content</h4>

<p>Phishing emails – those fraudulent messages that try to trick you into giving passwords or money – have been around for decades, but AI is supercharging their quality and quantity. With AI language models, a scammer can now generate tailored, grammatically perfect, and context-specific messages by the hundreds.</p>

<p>Europol (the EU’s police agency) warned in 2023 that ChatGPT’s ability to produce highly realistic text with ease makes it a powerful tool for criminals<sup id="fnref:48"><a href="#fn:48" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">48</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="surveillance-and-policing">Surveillance and Policing</h2>

<p>AI technologies are increasingly employed in surveillance and law enforcement, raising profound ethical issues around privacy, civil liberties, accuracy, and potential abuse of power.</p>

<h3 id="mass-surveillance-and-privacy-erosion">Mass Surveillance and Privacy Erosion</h3>

<p>In authoritarian contexts especially, AI-powered surveillance has been used to oppress and control populations. The starkest example is <strong>Xinjiang, China</strong>, where an estimated million-plus Uyghur Muslims have been subjected to high-tech repression. The Chinese government has deployed a “high-tech network of surveillance” in the region, including ubiquitous cameras with facial recognition, mandatory biometric data collection (DNA, iris scans), and phone/computer data monitoring – all fed into AI systems that flag “suspicious” behaviour<sup id="fnref:49"><a href="#fn:49" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">49</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Even outside such extreme cases, the spread of facial recognition in public spaces is blurring the line between security and privacy. There have been at least three known wrongful arrests of Black individuals in the US due to faulty face recognition matches<sup id="fnref:50"><a href="#fn:50" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">50</a></sup><sup id="fnref:51"><a href="#fn:51" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">51</a></sup>. One case was <strong>Robert Williams in Detroit</strong>: facial recognition misidentified him as a suspect, leading to his arrest and jailing for a crime he didn’t commit. Detroit later settled his lawsuit with a $300k payment and agreed to change its policies<sup id="fnref:52"><a href="#fn:52" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">52</a></sup><sup id="fnref:53"><a href="#fn:53" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">53</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="predictive-policing-and-bias">Predictive Policing and Bias</h3>

<p>Another use of AI in law enforcement is predictive analytics – algorithms that analyse crime data to predict where crimes might occur or who might be involved. While it might sound objective, these systems can perpetuate existing biases in policing data. “Bias in, bias out” applies strongly here.</p>

<p>Simply put, if your AI might ruin someone’s life, double-check it.</p>

<h2 id="employment-hiring-and-workplace-monitoring">Employment, Hiring, and Workplace Monitoring</h2>

<h3 id="ai-in-hiring--fairness-and-transparency">AI in Hiring – Fairness and Transparency</h3>

<p>Companies are increasingly using AI tools to screen job applicants, parse resumes, or even conduct video interviews with algorithmic analysis of facial expressions and tone. The promise is efficiency and objectivity; the peril is encoding bias and opacity in how employment decisions are made.</p>

<p>This lack of transparency and potential for discrimination has prompted regulatory attention. The <strong>EU AI Act</strong> will treat AI in employment as “high-risk,” requiring that such systems be proven non-discriminatory, transparent, and subject to human oversight<sup id="fnref:54"><a href="#fn:54" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">54</a></sup><sup id="fnref:55"><a href="#fn:55" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">55</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="workplace-monitoring-and-algorithmic-management">Workplace Monitoring and “Algorithmic Management”</h3>

<p>Employers have always monitored performance, but AI takes it to new levels of intrusiveness and automation. <strong>Amazon</strong> is the poster child of this trend: in its warehouses, an AI-driven system tracks each worker’s productivity in real time – items scanned, packing speed, “time off task” down to the minute<sup id="fnref:56"><a href="#fn:56" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">56</a></sup><sup id="fnref:57"><a href="#fn:57" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">57</a></sup>.</p>

<p>If a worker’s metrics fall below a target, the system will automatically generate warnings and even termination notices without a manager’s input<sup id="fnref:58"><a href="#fn:58" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">58</a></sup><sup id="fnref:59"><a href="#fn:59" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">59</a></sup>. Documents revealed that over a little more than a year, a single Amazon warehouse fired about <strong>300 employees (10% of staff)</strong> purely for productivity shortfalls as decided by this automated system<sup id="fnref:60"><a href="#fn:60" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">60</a></sup><sup id="fnref:61"><a href="#fn:61" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">61</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="military-and-geopolitical-applications">Military and Geopolitical Applications</h2>

<p>Perhaps the most grave domain of AI ethics is its use in warfare and geopolitical power struggles. AI is becoming integral to military systems, intelligence analysis, and autonomous weapons – raising existential questions about lethal decision-making by machines and the stability of global peace.</p>

<h3 id="autonomous-weapons-killer-robots">Autonomous Weapons (“Killer Robots”)</h3>

<p>One of the biggest debates is over <strong>Lethal Autonomous Weapons Systems (LAWS)</strong> – weapons that can select and engage targets without human intervention. The ethical issues here are immense. First, there’s the question of human control: delegating life-and-death decisions to algorithms arguably crosses a moral line, as machines lack human judgment, empathy, and accountability<sup id="fnref:62"><a href="#fn:62" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">62</a></sup><sup id="fnref:63"><a href="#fn:63" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">63</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Because of these issues, over 30 countries and numerous NGOs have called for a preemptive ban on killer robots (through campaigns like “Stop Killer Robots”), akin to bans on chemical or biological weapons. In 2015, thousands of AI researchers signed an open letter warning that autonomous weapons could be “the third revolution in warfare” (after gunpowder and nuclear arms)<sup id="fnref:64"><a href="#fn:64" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">64</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="ai-arms-race-and-geopolitical-tensions">AI Arms Race and Geopolitical Tensions</h3>

<p>We are witnessing an AI arms race in a broader sense: countries pouring resources into military AI for intelligence, cyber warfare, and autonomous systems. This race raises geopolitical ethical questions: will AI make wars more likely by giving some nations confidence in quick, decisive tech-driven victory?</p>

<h2 id="regulatory-outlook">Regulatory Outlook</h2>

<p>The ethical implications of AI span the environmental to the existential. A few clear themes emerge:</p>

<h3 id="transparency-and-accountability">Transparency and Accountability</h3>

<p>Whether it’s training data composition, model decision-making, or AI usage in hiring/policing, openness is critical. We’ve seen that when AI operates as a black box, trust erodes and harms go unmitigated. The <strong>EU’s AI Act</strong> is a significant step in this direction, introducing traceability and oversight requirements<sup id="fnref:65"><a href="#fn:65" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">65</a></sup><sup id="fnref:66"><a href="#fn:66" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">66</a></sup>.</p>

<h3 id="fairness-and-human-centric-design">Fairness and Human-Centric Design</h3>

<p>AI must be designed and deployed to augment human capabilities and decision-making, not to entrench inequalities or replace human values. The concept of <strong>AI ethics by design</strong> is gaining traction – similar to privacy by design – where equity and fairness checks are baked into the development process from the start.</p>

<h3 id="empowerment-vs-control">Empowerment vs. Control</h3>

<p>There is a fundamental tension between AI’s use to empower users/workers/citizens and its use to control or manipulate them. Ethical AI development leans towards empowerment – using AI to help rather than surveil; giving users more control rather than covertly nudging their behaviour.</p>

<h3 id="global-collaboration-and-norms">Global Collaboration and Norms</h3>

<p>AI’s challenges are global – carbon emitted in one country warms the whole planet; a deepfake in one language can influence another country’s politics; an arms race benefits no nation in the end. Thus, global governance and cooperation are key.</p>

<h3 id="continuous-oversight-and-adaptation">Continuous Oversight and Adaptation</h3>

<p>AI technology evolves quickly. Ethical and regulatory approaches must be agile and updated regularly. One innovative idea is the creation of <strong>AI oversight bodies</strong> – national or regional “AI Agencies” that specialise in monitoring AI developments and advising on policy.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Finally, it’s worth emphasising the human element. AI, for all the talk of autonomy, ultimately reflects human choices – in what objectives we set, what data we feed it, and where we apply it. As AI becomes more powerful, those choices have ever greater impact.</p>

<p>It falls on us – developers, policymakers, business leaders, and society at large – to wield AI in service of human dignity, equity, and prosperity. As the saying goes, with great power comes great responsibility. AI is indeed great power. This article has highlighted some of the responsibilities that come with it.</p>

<p>Navigating the ethical challenges will not be easy, but with informed, global and multidisciplinary engagement, we can ensure AI remains a tool for good – amplifying the best of human ingenuity, not the worst of our biases or greed.</p>

<p><strong>In the end, AI is merely a mirror for human choices—albeit a gigantic, turbo-charged one. With vigilance and humility, we might just keep the mirror cracked but functional rather than shattered.</strong></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Training GPT-3 used 1,287 MWh, 550 tons CO₂ <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Data centers water usage for cooling servers <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Data centers 1.5% of global electricity in 2024 <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>Doubling by 2030 due to AI growth <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Japan annual electricity consumption comparison <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>AI servers ~15% of data center energy <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p>Major tech hubs 85% consumption <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:8">
      <p>Inference 90% of AI model lifecycle energy <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:9">
      <p>OpenAI’s Kenyan moderators paid &lt;$2/hour for toxic content labeling <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:10">
      <p>Psychological trauma reported by moderators <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:11">
      <p>Mental health damage from graphic content exposure <a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:12">
      <p>Lawsuits over exploitative conditions <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:13">
      <p>Low pay and inadequate support documentation <a href="#fnref:13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:14">
      <p>Authors sued OpenAI over books used in training without permission <a href="#fnref:14" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:15">
      <p>Michael Chabon, Jodi Picoult and George R.R. Martin lawsuit <a href="#fnref:15" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:16">
      <p>ChatGPT summarizing and imitating writing styles <a href="#fnref:16" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:17">
      <p>Class actions by authors and publishers <a href="#fnref:17" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:18">
      <p>Visual artists against generative AI companies <a href="#fnref:18" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:19">
      <p>Artists’ class action against Stability AI <a href="#fnref:19" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:20">
      <p>5 billion scraped images in LAION dataset <a href="#fnref:20" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:21">
      <p>Thomson Reuters v ROSS court decision 2025 <a href="#fnref:21" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:22">
      <p>AI training use not fair use ruling <a href="#fnref:22" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:23">
      <p>Search tool repackaging original texts <a href="#fnref:23" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:24">
      <p>Harm to copyright owner’s market <a href="#fnref:24" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:25">
      <p>EU AI Act copyrighted material disclosure <a href="#fnref:25" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:26">
      <p>AI developers transparency requirements <a href="#fnref:26" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:27">
      <p>ChatGPT training data summaries requirement <a href="#fnref:27" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:28">
      <p>OpenAI’s GPT-4 report gave no info on data or training <a href="#fnref:28" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:29">
      <p>Competition and safety concerns cited <a href="#fnref:29" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:30">
      <p>Impossible to evaluate biases without data knowledge <a href="#fnref:30" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:31">
      <p>Amazon’s AI hiring tool penalised “women’s” in resumes <a href="#fnref:31" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:32">
      <p>Tech industry male dominance in training data <a href="#fnref:32" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:33">
      <p>Discrimination against women’s organizations <a href="#fnref:33" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:34">
      <p>Downgrading women’s college graduates <a href="#fnref:34" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:35">
      <p>Amazon engineers unable to guarantee no discrimination <a href="#fnref:35" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:36">
      <p>Project eventually scrapped due to bias issues <a href="#fnref:36" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:37">
      <p>ProPublica COMPAS system investigation findings <a href="#fnref:37" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:38">
      <p>72% Americans prefer AI development slowdown <a href="#fnref:38" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:39">
      <p>Only 8% want AI development to speed up <a href="#fnref:39" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:40">
      <p>Gary Marcus on Big Tech “moral descent” <a href="#fnref:40" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:41">
      <p>Profit over society prioritization <a href="#fnref:41" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:42">
      <p>98% of deepfakes online are pornographic, targeting women <a href="#fnref:42" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:43">
      <p>Facebook’s engagement algorithm boosts divisive content <a href="#fnref:43" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:44">
      <p>Algorithm changes preferentially boost anger reactions <a href="#fnref:44" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:45">
      <p>Arizona mother AI voice cloning scam <a href="#fnref:45" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:46">
      <p>Daughter’s voice perfectly mimicked for kidnapping hoax <a href="#fnref:46" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:47">
      <p>McAfee survey on voice cloning detection <a href="#fnref:47" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:48">
      <p>Europol warning about ChatGPT enabling realistic phishing <a href="#fnref:48" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:49">
      <p>China’s AI surveillance of Uyghurs with facial recognition <a href="#fnref:49" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:50">
      <p>Three wrongful arrests via face recognition in US <a href="#fnref:50" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:51">
      <p>Facial recognition accuracy issues for people of colour <a href="#fnref:51" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:52">
      <p>Robert Williams Detroit wrongful arrest case <a href="#fnref:52" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:53">
      <p>$300k settlement and policy changes <a href="#fnref:53" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:54">
      <p>EU AI Act high-risk employment classification <a href="#fnref:54" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:55">
      <p>Non-discriminatory and transparent requirements <a href="#fnref:55" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:56">
      <p>Amazon’s automated warehouse productivity system <a href="#fnref:56" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:57">
      <p>Real-time worker tracking and metrics <a href="#fnref:57" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:58">
      <p>Automatic warnings and termination notices <a href="#fnref:58" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:59">
      <p>No manager input required for disciplinary action <a href="#fnref:59" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:60">
      <p>300+ employees fired in single warehouse <a href="#fnref:60" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:61">
      <p>10% of staff terminated by automated system <a href="#fnref:61" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:62">
      <p>Autonomous weapons dehumanise decision-making <a href="#fnref:62" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:63">
      <p>Machines lack human judgment and accountability <a href="#fnref:63" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:64">
      <p>2015 open letter warning about autonomous weapons <a href="#fnref:64" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:65">
      <p>EU AI Act traceability requirements <a href="#fnref:65" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:66">
      <p>Oversight and transparency mandates <a href="#fnref:66" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="artificial-intelligence" /><category term="ethics" /><category term="technology" /><category term="ai-ethics" /><category term="machine-learning" /><category term="bias" /><category term="surveillance" /><category term="automation" /><category term="regulation" /><category term="environmental-impact" /><category term="copyright" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Artificial intelligence has catapulted from the plaything of graduate students to the digital weather system that now soaks every corner of the economy. The upsides are dazzling; the downsides, well, they're the reason you're reading this article instead of a holiday brochure.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-23-ethics-in-artificial-intelligence/ai-ethics.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4001/assets/images/posts/2025-07-23-ethics-in-artificial-intelligence/ai-ethics.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Can’t We Be Friends? The University Collaboration Paradox</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/20/why-cant-we-be-friends/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Can’t We Be Friends? The University Collaboration Paradox" /><published>2025-07-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/20/why-cant-we-be-friends</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/20/why-cant-we-be-friends/"><![CDATA[<p>British universities have a peculiar relationship with collaboration. They’ll partner for research grants, share libraries, and even run joint degree programmes—right up until the moment they need to compete for the same students, staff, or funding. It’s like watching neighbours share garden tools while simultaneously building higher fences.</p>

<h2 id="the-collaboration-paradox">The Collaboration Paradox</h2>

<p>Every university mission statement mentions collaboration. Every strategic plan promises partnerships. Every vice-chancellor’s speech includes paeans to “working together for the greater good.” Yet when push comes to shove, institutions guard their independence more fiercely than medieval city-states.</p>

<p>This paradox becomes most visible during crises. Universities facing financial difficulties prefer cutting jobs to sharing costs, despite the obvious economies of scale available through collaboration.</p>

<h2 id="where-cooperation-actually-works">Where Cooperation Actually Works</h2>

<p>Some areas show what’s possible:</p>

<p><strong>Library Consortiums:</strong> Universities have successfully shared catalogue systems and resources for decades. Students can access materials across multiple institutions, and costs are shared efficiently.</p>

<p><strong>Research Networks:</strong> Multi-institutional research centres demonstrate how collaboration can tackle problems too large for any single university.</p>

<p><strong>Shared Services:</strong> Some universities already collaborate on IT infrastructure, procurement, and administrative functions—proving the concept works when institutions commit to it.</p>

<h2 id="the-barriers-to-friendship">The Barriers to Friendship</h2>

<p><strong>Ranking Competition:</strong> League tables pit universities against each other, making collaboration feel like weakness rather than strength.</p>

<p><strong>Brand Protection:</strong> Each institution wants to protect its unique identity and market position.</p>

<p><strong>Governance Complexity:</strong> Collaborative decisions require multiple approval processes, slowing everything down.</p>

<p><strong>Resource Jealousy:</strong> Nobody wants to share their best facilities or staff with competitors.</p>

<h2 id="a-modest-proposal">A Modest Proposal</h2>

<p>Instead of competing to be the “best” university in narrow rankings, what if institutions competed to be the best collaborators? Imagine league tables that measured:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Successful partnership outcomes</li>
  <li>Shared resource efficiency</li>
  <li>Cross-institutional student mobility</li>
  <li>Joint research impact</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-scottish-model">The Scottish Model</h2>

<p>Scotland’s universities demonstrate what’s possible. Despite fierce competition, they’ve managed successful collaboration on admissions (UCAS), quality assurance, and international marketing. The result? A stronger sector overall.</p>

<h2 id="why-it-matters">Why It Matters</h2>

<p>The current crisis in higher education funding makes collaboration not just desirable but essential. Universities can either work together to find solutions or watch each other struggle separately.</p>

<p>The choice seems obvious. The implementation, unfortunately, remains as elusive as ever.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Universities are better together—when they remember that their real competition isn’t each other, but irrelevance. Perhaps it’s time to turn those mission statement promises into actual policies.</p>

<p>After all, in an uncertain world, the best institutional strategy might just be having good friends.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="university-partnerships" /><category term="university-cooperation" /><category term="collaboration" /><category term="institutional-partnerships" /><category term="competition" /><category term="higher-education-sector" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Universities compete fiercely while claiming to collaborate generously. It's time to examine why the sector's most obvious solution—working together—remains frustratingly elusive.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Cooperation" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=University+Cooperation" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rightsizing Rant: When Corporate Jargon Eats Reality</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/15/rightsizing-rant/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rightsizing Rant: When Corporate Jargon Eats Reality" /><published>2025-07-15T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-15T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/15/rightsizing-rant</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/15/rightsizing-rant/"><![CDATA[<p>The word “rightsizing” has slithered into British universities like a particularly obnoxious management consultant. It’s the sort of term that sounds vaguely positive—after all, who could argue with making something the <em>right</em> size?—while simultaneously describing the wholesale demolition of entire departments. It’s linguistic chloroform: designed to make unpleasant realities smell faintly of success rather than redundancy notices.</p>

<h2 id="the-euphemism-treadmill">The Euphemism Treadmill</h2>

<p>“Rightsizing” joins a distinguished pantheon of corporate doublespeak designed to make bad news sound like strategic brilliance. Its ancestors include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>“Restructuring”</strong> (firing people)</li>
  <li><strong>“Optimisation”</strong> (firing people more efficiently)</li>
  <li><strong>“Transformation”</strong> (firing people while pivoting)</li>
  <li><strong>“Streamlining”</strong> (firing people, but sleekly)</li>
</ul>

<p>Each iteration becomes more elaborate as the previous euphemism gets contaminated by reality. Soon we’ll need “strategic talent realignment initiatives” just to describe laying off the catering staff.</p>

<h2 id="how-rightsizing-actually-works">How Rightsizing Actually Works</h2>

<p>The rightsizing process typically unfolds as follows:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Phase One: Discovery.</strong> Senior management discovers the university employs actual human beings, who inconveniently require salaries.</li>
  <li><strong>Phase Two: Consultation.</strong> Expensive consultants arrive to recommend firing the people who actually know how things work.</li>
  <li><strong>Phase Three: Communication.</strong> Staff receive emails explaining how losing their jobs will “unlock transformational efficiencies.”</li>
  <li><strong>Phase Four: Implementation.</strong> The university becomes smaller, poorer, and somehow less capable of doing what it was supposed to do in the first place.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="the-jargon-ecosystem">The Jargon Ecosystem</h2>

<p>Rightsizing rarely travels alone. It brings friends:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>“Agile structures”</strong> (fewer people doing more jobs)</li>
  <li><strong>“Enhanced productivity”</strong> (the same output with half the staff)</li>
  <li><strong>“Sustainable footprint”</strong> (sustainable for the budget, fatal for morale)</li>
  <li><strong>“Future-ready organisation”</strong> (ready for a future with no employees)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="why-this-matters-beyond-academic-circles">Why This Matters Beyond Academic Circles</h2>

<p>Universities aren’t widget factories. When you rightsize a philosophy department, you don’t just lose efficiency—you lose institutional memory, research relationships, and the kind of intellectual continuity that makes universities more than just degree-printing machines.</p>

<p>The real tragedy is that rightsizing often creates more problems than it solves. Fewer people means longer delays, reduced innovation, and the gradual transformation of universities into administrative processing centres rather than centres of learning and discovery.</p>

<h2 id="the-alternative-actual-english">The Alternative: Actual English</h2>

<p>Instead of rightsizing, why not try:</p>
<ul>
  <li>“We’re making redundancies”</li>
  <li>“We’re cutting staff”</li>
  <li>“We’re reducing our workforce”</li>
</ul>

<p>Revolutionary concept: describing reality using words that actually mean what they describe.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion-size-matters-but-so-does-honesty">Conclusion: Size Matters, But So Does Honesty</h2>

<p>If universities must shrink, they should at least have the courtesy to call it what it is. Rightsizing is corporate-speak designed to make administrators feel better about difficult decisions while making everyone else feel like they’re living in a dystopian novel where words have been drained of meaning.</p>

<p>The next time someone mentions rightsizing, ask them to translate. You might be surprised by what you find lurking beneath the jargon.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="corporate-language" /><category term="management" /><category term="rightsizing" /><category term="corporate-jargon" /><category term="university-management" /><category term="redundancies" /><category term="business-speak" /><category term="euphemisms" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When 'rightsizing' becomes the euphemism du jour for mass redundancies, you know corporate-speak has officially jumped the shark. Let's decode the jargon that's chloroforming common sense.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=Corporate+Jargon" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=Corporate+Jargon" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Flatpacks Not Ivory Towers: Why Universities Should Be Built Like IKEA Furniture</title><link href="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/10/flatpacks-not-ivory-towers/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Flatpacks Not Ivory Towers: Why Universities Should Be Built Like IKEA Furniture" /><published>2025-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2025-07-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4001/2025/07/10/flatpacks-not-ivory-towers</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4001/2025/07/10/flatpacks-not-ivory-towers/"><![CDATA[<p>Universities are constructed like medieval cathedrals: magnificent, permanent, and requiring decades to build. But perhaps it’s time to embrace the IKEA approach: modular components, clear instructions, and the ability to disassemble and rebuild when circumstances change.</p>

<h2 id="the-cathedral-model-vs-the-flatpack-approach">The Cathedral Model vs. The Flatpack Approach</h2>

<p><strong>Traditional Universities (The Cathedral):</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Permanent departments carved in administrative stone</li>
  <li>Hierarchical structures that haven’t changed since the 1960s</li>
  <li>Massive overhead for specialized functions</li>
  <li>Nearly impossible to reorganize without institutional trauma</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Flatpack Universities (The IKEA Model):</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Flexible, reconfigurable academic units</li>
  <li>Shared services across multiple functions</li>
  <li>Rapid assembly and disassembly as needed</li>
  <li>Clear instructions for organizational change</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-modular-advantage">The Modular Advantage</h2>

<p><strong>Academic Modules:</strong> Instead of fixed departments, universities could operate with flexible academic clusters that form and reform based on research needs and student demand.</p>

<p><strong>Service Modules:</strong> Shared administrative functions across institutions—HR, finance, IT—that can be plugged in as needed.</p>

<p><strong>Infrastructure Modules:</strong> Physical and digital resources that can be scaled up or down without massive capital investment.</p>

<h2 id="case-study-the-stuck-drawer-problem">Case Study: The Stuck Drawer Problem</h2>

<p>Every IKEA veteran knows the frustration of a drawer that won’t slide properly. Universities have the same problem: departments that don’t fit together, services that can’t communicate, and processes that jam under pressure.</p>

<p>The difference is that with flatpack furniture, you can take it apart and reassemble it correctly. Universities prefer to live with the stuck drawer for decades.</p>

<h2 id="the-assembly-instructions-universities-need">The Assembly Instructions Universities Need</h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Standardized Interfaces:</strong> Like USB ports, university systems should connect easily with minimal adaptation.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Plug-and-Play Partnerships:</strong> Collaborations should be as simple as connecting two IKEA units with the standard fixtures.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>User-Friendly Manuals:</strong> University processes should be comprehensible to people who didn’t design them.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Quality Control:</strong> Regular checks to ensure all components are working as intended.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="why-this-matters">Why This Matters</h2>

<p>The current model forces universities to choose between:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Maintaining expensive, underused specialized functions</li>
  <li>Outsourcing everything to private companies</li>
  <li>Going without essential services</li>
</ul>

<p>A modular approach offers a third option: sharing high-quality services across multiple institutions while maintaining institutional identity.</p>

<h2 id="the-swedish-paradox">The Swedish Paradox</h2>

<p>IKEA succeeds by combining standardization with personalization. You get standard components but arrange them to suit your space and needs. Universities could learn from this: shared back-office functions combined with distinctive academic missions.</p>

<h2 id="objections-and-allen-keys">Objections and Allen Keys</h2>

<p><strong>“But universities aren’t furniture!”</strong> True, but they are organizations, and organizations benefit from thoughtful design principles.</p>

<p><strong>“Academic freedom requires independence!”</strong> Shared administrative services don’t threaten academic freedom any more than shared electricity providers threaten your choice of reading lamp.</p>

<p><strong>“This will create bland uniformity!”</strong> IKEA somehow manages to supply millions of homes while allowing individual expression. Universities could do the same.</p>

<h2 id="implementation-some-assembly-required">Implementation: Some Assembly Required</h2>

<p>The transition wouldn’t happen overnight, but universities could start with:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Pilot shared service programs</li>
  <li>Standardized interfaces between systems</li>
  <li>Modular degree program design</li>
  <li>Cross-institutional staff mobility</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="conclusion-instructions-included">Conclusion: Instructions Included</h2>

<p>The university sector’s problems aren’t unsolvable—they’re assembly problems. The pieces exist; they just need to be put together more thoughtfully.</p>

<p>And unlike actual IKEA furniture, universities don’t come with a little bag of spare screws. They have to create their own.</p>]]></content><author><name>Justin O'Brien</name></author><category term="higher-education" /><category term="university-structure" /><category term="organizational-design" /><category term="university-organization" /><category term="modular-design" /><category term="institutional-efficiency" /><category term="academic-structure" /><category term="organizational-flexibility" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Universities are built like medieval cathedrals when they should be assembled like flatpack furniture. Modular, efficient, and possible to rebuild when you inevitably lose the instructions.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=Modular+Universities" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://via.placeholder.com/800x400/6069c7/ffffff?text=Modular+Universities" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>